<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The new earth, or, The true Magna Charta of the past ages, and of the ages or world to come: called The Jews commonweal. Written by an unworthy witness of the truth of the great God, John Brayne.</title>
            <author>Brayne, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E714_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E714[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The new earth, or, The true Magna Charta of the past ages, and of the ages or world to come: called The Jews commonweal. Written by an unworthy witness of the truth of the great God, John Brayne.</title>
                  <author>Brayne, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Moon, at the seven stars in Paul's Church-yard, neer the great North-door.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 2d"; "Octob: ye 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Seekers (Sect) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Millenialism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jewish law --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118573:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEW EARTH, OR, The True <hi>MAGNA CHARTA</hi> OF The paſt AGES, and of the AGES or World to come: CALLED The JEWS COMMONWEAL. Written by an unworthy witneſs of the truth of the great God, <hi>JOHN BRAYNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 42.21.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord is well pleaſed for his righteouſneſs ſake: he will magnifie the law, and make it honourable.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Moon, featuring a crescent moon with a face, and seven stars</figDesc>
               <p>Richard in Paules Church Yard Att The</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moon,</hi> at the ſeven ſtars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the great North-door. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118573:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118573:2"/>
            <head>To the Supreme Authority, THE PARLIAMENT OF THE Commonwealth of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He men without law, that is, the Nations to whom God had not given the knowledge thereof, were a law unto themſelves, and made laws of their own, wherein one man became as a God to another; but we which have the law of God, and uſe it not as a law, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in a kind as thoſe Gentiles were, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without it, or worſe, who by our traditions (for ſo indeed are humane laws) have made voide the laws of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: thus the Phariſees had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorized the law of God before us. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:118573:3"/>the ceremonial law, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.8. and the moral law, <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. by which then, as now, the word of God was made of none effect, <hi>v.</hi> 13. and was committed in many things, beſides theſe particulars that are ſet down and expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when man and not God reigneth: nor doth God, whiles his laws judge us not, judge, but man; the law of the Nation, and not of God: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till men are judged by Gods law, judgement is not the Lords, but <hi>Justinians, Gratians,</hi> or other mens; upon which the people imploy their time and ſtudy: but if Gods laws were ſet up among us, by his Bible or Statute book, every man would eaſily become a lawyer; where no acts are ever to be repealed, but out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt thoſe of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> No word muſt be added or diminiſhed; there is therein no more or leſs then ſhould be; ſo full hath God made it, to govern by, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.1, 2, 6, 8. the Ruler of the people was to have it alway by him, and not to turn from the right hand or the left, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18, 19, 20. It was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of the Heathens, they knew not the law to make uſe thereof; it was the wickedneſs of the Papacy, that it was not uſed therein, though
<pb facs="tcp:118573:3"/>they knew it, they well ſeeing, that both they and their practice were under the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; and that they had no authority thence to ſet up themſelves, and Lord it over the world, putting themſelves in the place of God, without God.</p>
            <p>But yee, O yee Princes of the people, into whoſe hearts God put it to give aſſurances to the nation that your deſire is to make it happy, which the Lord tells you conſiſts in ſetting up Gods law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. God hath laid ingagements on you, as on his people of old, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.24. though other alterations in the State were troubleſome, God will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper you in this and in your undertakings; for this, remember ye have the ingagements of men upon you, and of God on you, and of vows made to God on your own ſouls. O what ſhall or can hinder! you need not fit a day to do it, it is done for you to a word, in the word: untill when, nationally we are not the people of God. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.12. tells us there is but one law-giver; conſider then what it is to give a law that is not according to Gods, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when we have the law by us, and are not to go to heaven or beyond the Seas for
<pb facs="tcp:118573:4"/>it; and I pray conſider, that the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. though they had laws of their own to judge by, yet not having Gods law, they are ſaid to be without law: and obſerve well thence what God may ſay of us, our law and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Do, O do as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> did, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.2, 3. bring forth the law, do you and your people make a covenant, and all the people, with God, to reſtore and obey the law in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the ſtatutes, and judgements thereof; ſo ſhall no injuſtice nor oppreſſion be uſed in the land; this is the <hi>New Earth</hi> which the Saints even in the Apoſtles dayes dayes look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, in which dwelleth righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. the Romans having deſtroyed that government before, and hath laine hid to this day in the word; untill which, the foundations of judgement and juſtice being out of courſe, though you are never ſo wiſe, juſt, and willing to do the nation good, ye cannot, for the foundations are out of courſe, and what can the righteous do? ſaith <hi>David.</hi> And let not the cry of the Prophet take hold of you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.16. <hi>Vp, Lord, for men have made void thy law.</hi> Examine, I pray, if your
<pb facs="tcp:118573:4"/>laws have not in ſome kinde made void Gods laws, which is the greateſt guilt of a nation that may be, under which we have layn ever ſince we had the knowledge of it amongſt us. Give me leave to tell you, It is not enough you have put down the power and authority, but you muſt put down the rule of the fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy alſo, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. O that ye might be honoured of God, to put down that, and ſet up the Lord, and not your own, when indeed ye ſhall be healers of the nation, and reſtorers of the paths to walk in; on which I beſeech you to look, as on that is Gods work, and your chiefeſt duty to ſet up judges in the right place of judgement; that they judge according to the law, that judgement may be indeed the Lords, and they called gods; in which you ſhall do more for the nation then all the Parliaments ever were; and deliver your own ſouls, make proſperous the people, eſtabliſh authority and rule, compoſe the differences in being among us, and make the people one; for it muſt be God that muſt make thoſe of one houſe, much more thoſe of one nation to agree,
<pb facs="tcp:118573:5"/>whereby ye may onely do it: to which I leave you, and pray the Lord to help you and direct you therein, and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A faithful ſervant and well-wiſher of you all in the Lord,</hi> John Brayne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118573:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE foundation of all the gracious dealings of God with men, hath alwayes been laid and began in or with Covenants; in which God takes a people, as a man a woman, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſeth them to himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.8. &amp; 24.3. &amp; 7. where in ſtead of the blood of the ſacrifice, we have Chriſt to make it in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is the firſt covenant; the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator or Miniſter thereof was <hi>Moſes;</hi> which was legal, and made with all the people, That they ſhould keep the commandments, the Statutes, and Judgements ſet down in the books of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 5. &amp; <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. The bleſſings of this covenant were temporal, for this life: when it was broken, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bleſſings were withdrawn. The Kings of Iſrael, as <hi>Joſiah</hi> (2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 23.2, 3.) renewed it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.17. And another then this legal covenant, was not made with the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or people of the Jews, by <hi>Moſes, Jer.</hi> 7.22, 23, 24. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 8. ult. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There was a new covenant; in which, not <hi>Moſes,</hi> but Chriſt is the Mediator; which is a <hi>better covenant,</hi> having not the law <hi>written in tables of ſtone,</hi> but <hi>in the heart,</hi> Heb. 8.10. which had <hi>better promiſes,</hi> verſ. 6. and Chriſt ſaid to be <hi>a Prieſt of good things to come:</hi> which was only made with believers in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in whom the law is kept only and indeed; in ſhadow of which, God, after covenanting with him in the Moſaical
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118573:6"/>covenant, he gave <hi>Aarons</hi> Prieſthood, from <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note.</hi> As a Nation cannot ſubſiſt without rule and government, in any order, nor be without food and raiment, nor continue or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, if God curſe them, and bleſs them not; ſo it is neceſſary for theſe, that a National Covenant be made with God by us, for the binding our ſelves to God, to keep his commandments, Statutes, and Judgements; and is as neceſſary for us, as ever it was for the Jews: by which God becomes engagedly the God of a Nation, and they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his people, and not nationally as before: for, by the new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, God is not the God of a nation, but of believers onely in a nation, joyned to Chriſt in the way of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The New covenant implyes, God hath made the firſt Old; and that which decayeth and waxeth old, is ready to vaniſh,</hi> Heb. 8.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> As Chriſt and <hi>Moſes</hi> deſtroyed not one another, nor the Goſpel deſtroyes not the law: ſo nor doth one covenant deſtroy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, nor is the firſt covenant old, but to thoſe only that are in the ſecond; in which the firſt is as it were ſwallowed up or received into: But to thoſe that are onely under the firſt, To them the firſt is ſo, as if there were not a ſecond; and thoſe under the ſecond are ſo under that, as if the firſt were not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note.</hi> Men are to be firſt under the firſt, or <hi>Sinai;</hi> and thence come to <hi>Sion, Heb.</hi> 12.18, 22. and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> is <hi>a Schoolmaſter to bring us to Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 4.24. Rom. 9.4. Heb. 9.15. &amp; 12.18, 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Illuſt.</hi> As in the beginning of the goverment of the Jews Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal, there was a rule ſet up for Judgement among the people, called judicial laws, to govern them by, in which was the Kingly goverment of God, and the law called the Royal: and there was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Levitical Law, which appertained to the ſervice of the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, in which Chriſts Prieſthood was ſet out, in things appertaining to God for the people; which diſtinct eſtates are in a kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved among us this day in the Church and State, As in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron:</hi> ſo now ſhould it be <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Romans</hi> conquering <hi>Judea,</hi> according to the prophecie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. they put down their rule and government, that they could put no man to death. Judgement was now altered into the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118573:6"/>cuſtoms of the heathens, and there ever ſince it hath continued: and no nation in the world ever ſince taking God, or God taking them to be his people, as of old; though lately we (in a wrong way) ſeemed to do it: for at the renewing of the covenant, the law and the ſtatutes and judgements were only read, and the people ingaging themſelves to keep them a never did any Goſpel-Church do any ſuch thing, nor ſhall ever do it, nor were they the Church-paterns. Antichriſts mark is ſet down to be (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.) one that is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>without law;</hi> that is, he exerciſeth not the law of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> up the covenant of the law; but brings all the world and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to one eſtate: which if he had not done, or if we do not do, we ſhall finde the one is as neceſſary among men in the world, as the other in the Church. And hence Antichriſts workings are called <hi>the myſtery</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of lawleſneſs,</hi> by whom the laws adminiſtrations are deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If we have this covenant, we muſt have circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Apoſtle clears it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The covenant that was confirmed</hi> (in circumciſion) <hi>before of God in Chriſt, the law which was four hundred and thirty yeers after, cannot diſannul.</hi> Now this covenant I ſpeak of, is diſtinguiſhed from that, by <hi>Moſes,</hi> thus, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.3. <hi>The Lord made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us</hi> (in Horeb) <hi>even us, who are all of us alive this day.</hi> John 7.22. <hi>Moſes gave you you circumciſion, not becauſe it is of</hi> Moſes, <hi>but of the fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>If this covenant be not ſufficient to make men ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of baptiſm, and whether men were not circumciſed by this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Men were not circumciſed by this, but that other covenant ſpoke of <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.3. and was long before this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Baptiſm belongs to the ſecond, not firſt covenant; in which God becomes our God, not by doing, but believing; not by works, but grace; not in <hi>Moſes,</hi> but Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Apoſtles required not this in their time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.13. They looked for <hi>a New Earth,</hi> that is, a reſtoration of that adminiſtration of the law to be; but not untill the fall of Antichriſts rule and government, being of the fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118573:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. The law was for the worlds government; that that they did, concerned the Church, and the new covenant onely, and not the world, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12, 13, 14, 15, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note.</hi> Both covenants are neceſſary, when they may be had; and without the covenants, is no promiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. the heathens were <hi>Aliens from the civil eſtate of Iſrael</hi> (Beza) <hi>and ſtrangers from the covenant of promiſe,</hi> ſpeaking of them both. And thus it is with us this day.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Judges.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The Lord hath promiſed he will <hi>reſtore Judges as at the firſt,</hi> Iſa. 1.26. and, in them, judgement: and it was the great wrath of God, that they were taken away out of the middeſt of the people, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.3. and would it not be a mercy if this people might have them, that never had them, as at the firſt? The firſt were of Gods inſtitution, and beſt; thoſe of other forms ſince, of men, and far worſe. O let our Judges be <hi>as at the firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> the firſt of Judges, by <hi>Jethro's</hi> advice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.16. diſſolved Monarchy in rule, laying it down, for his own and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eaſe: God conſenting thereunto, gave the people laws to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, and Judges to govern them by; who are deſcribed to the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.22. that they chuſe not amiſs: who in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the government, and after, were choſen of the people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.13. &amp; 16.18. for which ſervice men may be eaſily fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in that the law was daily read in the Synagogues, which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Prophets and wiſe men ſent of God to them; which cannot be done in our law: it was the Sabbath-work and ſervice of God to teach it daily in publike and private: and ſhall this law be thus laid aſide, neglected, and not ſtudied, for the bramble-rule of the world? and was ſubverted, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>Hear, ye Judges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1. <hi>If the controverſie come to judgement that they may judge, they muſt judge; Luk.</hi> 12.58. ye muſt judge the people with juſt judgement. <hi>Judge righteouſly between a man and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him,</hi> Deut. 1.16. verſ. 17. <hi>Ye ſhall not reſpect perſons. Ye ſhall not take a gift, for a gift doth blinde the eyes of the wiſe, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118573:7"/>pervert the words of the righteous,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.3, 5. Exod. 23.3. <hi>thou ſhalt countenance a poor man in his cauſe</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>thou ſhalt not wreſt the judgement of thy poor in his cauſe,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>thou ſhalt not oppreſs the ſtranger,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>keep thee far from a falſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the innocent and the righteous ſlay thou not,</hi> Prov. 28.21.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>
                     <hi>To theſe Judges ſet up in every City,</hi> 2 Chron. 19.5. Deut. 16.18. <hi>ſeventy two, called the</hi> Sanhedrin, <hi>were added, and joyned to them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. While <hi>Moſes</hi> lived, he ſupplyed their place, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.22. after him, <hi>Deborah, Samuel,</hi> and the reſt, ſucceeded <hi>Moſes,</hi> judging Iſrael in the difficult cauſes that others could not judge, being brought before them: God had eminently gifted and raiſed up ſome to rule, untill the time of the kings, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16, 17. or when theſe failed at any time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11. ſuch of the people as were thought to be moſt able and fit to judge, were ſet a part to judge the difficult caſes of the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.14. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8, 10. though ordinary perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Thoſe that judge juſtly for God,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He hath honoured before the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the ruler of thy people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. He eſtabliſheth that rule is according to his word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12. <hi>The man</hi> (in the difficult caſe) <hi>that will do preſumptuouſly, and not hearken to the Prieſt and Judge, that man ſhall dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. He encourageth them to go on, and fear not man, becauſe the <hi>judgement is the Lords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Herein is the ground of courage only.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If ye judge unjuſtly, the curſe of God and the people is on you.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.19. <hi>Curſed be he that perverteth the judgement of the ſtranger, fatherleſs, and widdow,</hi> verſ. 25. <hi>Curſed be he taketh a bribe to ſlay an innocent perſon,</hi> verſ. 26. <hi>Curſed be he confirmeth not all the words of this law to do them.</hi> Look what the Law ſaith, God fulfils.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118573:8"/>
               <head>Of Judgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WE are ſure the judgement of God is according to truth,</hi> Rom. 2.2. but not that mans is ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.7. Judgement is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to God, or is Gods, and is not mans: one man, of himſelf, cannot aſſume the authority; but in the way God hath ordained, and under God: and when he hath the authority, he hath it not, but to put in execution Gods law, if he have it, and his judgement; for judgement is the Lords, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. <hi>There is one law-giver, who is able to ſave and deſtroy.</hi> Who art thou that judgeſt another? <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The written word given the Jews for rule and government, is indeed the law; the rule and government of God and all Nations that rule not hereby, but by the work of that in their hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. As the effect depends on the cauſe, ſo the work of the law, on the law; if there had been no law, there had been no work of the law in men: (O diſtinguiſh between theſe:) our laws are but the work of the law, though the law hath wrought more ſtrongly on us then others, who had no knowledge of the letter of the law at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judgement ſhall be one to the ſtranger, and he that is of your own country,</hi> Lev. 24.22. and ſo is no place for civil law, or mixt laws of Nations with us: the ſmall are to be heard as well as the great, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17. every mans cauſe heard alike, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſs in judgement: thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; but in righteouſneſs ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour.</hi> They were not to take bribe or reward. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. Thus <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 16.15. ſo that tribute and cuſtom, I ſuppoſe, aroſe under the government of Kings, and was not under Judges, 1 <hi>Sam,</hi> 8.17.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>That judgement might run down as a ſtream, and be free to all as water, to every mans occaſions, and uncorrupt,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It was given in the language of the people, having many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes from God for obedience; which, by adhering to the law of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118573:8"/>Nations, men loſe: and it had many curſes added to diſobedience, which had place in the hearts of men, to keep them from breaking the law, and keeping them in obedience. O what law is like this, to do a people good, which cannot puniſh diſobedience with curſes, nor obedience with bleſſings, as God doth!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It was part of the worſhip of God, to have it read and expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the people; which cannot be of mans laws. That none ſhould be ignorant thereof, it was preached and taught at home and abroad, publike and private, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. to 16. and preſſed on the conſcience daily, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.49. <hi>This people that know not the law, are accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It was to be free, and coſt nothing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.22. It was to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in all time; that is, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever occaſion called on them to do juſtice: So that after the ſetting up of Judges, we have only two cauſes for which men were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ward, <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.34. which was onely for the difficulty of them, when that <hi>Moſes</hi> durſt not paſs ſentence before he had enquired of God what the judgement was; ſo careful was he in the matter of judgement, that it might be Gods, and not his, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. This cauſe is taken away now from us: for then the law was not revealed, but now it is, and we have the minde of God, ſo as that not a word muſt be added thereunto: and the Judge muſt not decline from the law in judgement neither to the right hand nor to the left, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Two Judges were appointed to be ſet in all the gates of the Cities in the land, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. ſo that the people were not forced to go far for law, that was neer them, in the word; nor for juſtice, it was at their doors.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Every knowing man was a lawyer, he needed none to plead his cauſe, it was laid down ſo plain, and ſtated ſo clear in the word by God for them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ap.</hi> Who now would leave the pure ſteams of juſtice that came out from God, and riſe in him, for the muddy ſtreams of <hi>Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Gratian,</hi> and other blind and ignorant men! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ap.</hi> Who would not ſubmit rather to that judgement that is Gods, then to that that is mans; and do as <hi>Paul,</hi> appeal to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118573:9"/>ſupream judgement, which is beyond <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and above it, if he might be tryed by it, which <hi>Paul</hi> could not then be?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What liberty would this bring to the nation! what freedome from expence in their eſtates, from impriſonments in their perſons, from being deceived in their cauſes, and from being overborn in their judgement! which, by delay of judgement, great men have much advantage offered them to: corrupt judges hinder juſtice, and get falſe witneſſes; and many condemned perſons eſcape puniſhment, and innocents by long impriſonment are undone in their eſtates, their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and repute among men.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Gods wrath for delay of juſtice, lyeth heavy on the nations daily; and <hi>wicked mens hearts are ſet in them to do evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that judgement is not executed ſpeedily on thoſe that do wickedly,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. <hi>He that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes <hi>law, dyed without mercy, under two or three witneſſes.</hi> Conſider now, how ſhall we, in keeping up another law then <hi>Moſes,</hi> to Judge the Nation by, free our ſouls from deſpiſing <hi>Moſes</hi> law!</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Joh. 7.51. <hi>Doth our law judge any man before it hear him, and know what he doth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the higher and weightier cauſes he was to judge of, he would not proceed, if he had not heard what to do in the matter from God (all the judges of the world ſhould take notice of this thing well) and conſider if it be not a dangerous thing to judge of any caſe contrary to the judgement God hath revealed in his law, or puniſh any man for a fault otherwayes then God hath ſet down; and where they are not, to deſiſt from judgement untill they have conſulted with God in his word what to do therein, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did. If they do otherwayes, whether they are not to give account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as well as he, to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>For clearing of what I have before laid down, and that that followeth, conſider with me four generals.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That thoſe are not under the rule and government of the law, in that way the law appoints, are thoſe the Scripture ſaith are <hi>without law;</hi> that is, without the publike exerciſe thereof and rule among them.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118573:9"/>
                  <p n="2">2. There is a being <hi>without the law;</hi> that is, all the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the law; as infants, ignorants, Atheiſts; of which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſaid of himſelf, that he was <hi>without the law:</hi> and this is from the ſence and underſtanding of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is a being under the law in the external government of it, in a Commonweal, and in the condition of the ſoul, as it is in unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. <hi>before faith came, we</hi> (even Jews and Gentiles) <hi>were ſhut up under the law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Thoſe under the law internally, are to be under the external form of the law, to be guided and inſtructed thereby, as by <hi>a Schoolmaſter to bring them to Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe without the law, are not freed from the law, though they are judged by another law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The Scripture hath ſhut up all men under ſin;</hi> that is, the law; even all thoſe which are without law, and thoſe under law alſo.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All which prove the law of God to be the rule to judge by, that it is indeed the <hi>Magna Charta, Suprema Lex,</hi> and <hi>Salus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli:</hi> and now only is judgement the Lords.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The ſecond General to clear that that followeth, is</head>
                  <p>Deut. 6.1. <hi>Theſe are the Commandments, the Statutes, and the Judgements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Commandments,</hi> I underſtand the 10 words given in two Tables by God to <hi>Moſes</hi> on <hi>Sinai,</hi> Exod. 20. which was the ground of Statutes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Statutes</hi> are the ſeveral caſes depending on each <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> and ariſing out of them, and ſet down to direct the Judges how to Judge according unto God, in the matters of God, laid down in the firſt Tables; and in matter of men, in the ſecond: they being the abſolute decrees of God, Judges and Judged muſt reſt in, from whence is no appeal; and is the ground of Judgement.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Judgement</hi> contains the ſentence added to the breach of every law for puniſhment, or to obedience of the law, for courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein, the promiſes of good and mercy, and is only proper to Gods law: and curſes added to his law, not mans; which is an empty law.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118573:10"/>
               <head>Third General.</head>
               <p n="1">I. That though in the 4 laſt books of <hi>Moſes</hi> is an oft repetition of the Statutes and Judgements, yet uſually there is inſerted in each of them ſome weighty diſtinction, and not without great reaſon repeated: which, becauſe of my neceſſity, and brevity of time of writing, with my other imployments, I have omitted to obſerve, leaving it to your ſelves to do, as being the ſole object of your ſtudy and rule of life to live by.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That as in the beginning God divided government, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the judicials, and other to <hi>Aaron</hi> in the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> government in the law is not deſtroyed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. and cap. 23.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Aarons</hi> Prieſthood, and with that his government, ceaſeth; and in the place thereof, Jeſus Chriſt, by the Fathers appointment, is ſet up. <hi>Heh.</hi> 7.11, 12, 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So that now as firſt there was <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſo now there is to be, to the end of the World, <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt, to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the World by.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Moſes</hi> in the World or State, under the covenant of works, alſo the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, ruling for him, becauſe he is not of he World.</item>
                  <item>2. Chriſt in the Church, among the Saints or believers, under the new covenant of grace, among whom the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is, being one of them.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">III. Thoſe words, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2. <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> cannot be ſaid of, nor applyed to, any in that way as the words are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but to thoſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That have covenanted with God in the way of the law, as the Iſraelites did.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That are under the rule and government of the commands, the Statutes and Judgements contained in that law.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>That was ſpoken only of thoſe God brought out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and concerns not us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> As the Jews were under the bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and were reſtrained from Gods ſervice, and were then not in covenant with him, nor had not his law to judge by; ſo we have been under Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118573:10"/>in Babel, and have been reſtrained from Gods ſervice, and were then not in covenant with the Lord, as they were not; nor is his law ſet up as a rule to judge by among us: ſo that when God ſhall have brought us out of Babel, and ſet up his laws, and brought us into covenant with himſelf, according to <hi>Moſes,</hi> it ſhall then be as binding to us, that God brought us out of Babel, as to them, that he brought them out of Egypt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.14.15. <hi>They ſhall no more ſay, The Lord liveth that brought them out of Egypt, but out of the north countryes,</hi> Jer. 23.7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Under the firſt covenant God was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> under the ſecond, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p>In the one, God is as <hi>Abram</hi> to <hi>Hagar,</hi> whoſe ſon ſhe had by him was to be caſt out under the Goſpel-eſtate; which was fulfilled in the caſting out of unbelievers from the ſociety of Saints, they being not to inherit the promiſe, that is Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. which work was then done, and ſhall be moſt certainly done againe in this age of ours. In the other, God is as <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Sarah,</hi> whoſe ſon <hi>Iſaac</hi> being born of the free-woman, ſignifieth the ſtate of the Church under the Goſpel, under the name of <hi>Jeruſalem from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> which are a ſociety of believers joyned to the Lord Jeſus in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, in whom the <hi>better promiſes</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and made over to the Saints, <hi>born after the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 4.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concluſion.</hi> The covenant of works was after the covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> of grace; but being renewed in Chriſt, it is called <hi>new,</hi> and the new old, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. The now firſt covenant, though it hath not the beſt, yet, it hath many excellent promiſes neceſſary for the life annexed to it; which we wanting, bodily are reduced to great neceſſities; and the breaking thereof brought ruine and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſuddainly to the Jews.</p>
               <p>And though at this time it be not in eſteem among men, yet the propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 42.19, 21. incourageth me, that after Gods ſervant comes, who the blind world accounts blind, though God ſaith he is his ſervant, and perfect, and which the Scripture before clearly ſhews was to come after the grand Apoſtacy of Antichriſt; I ſay, after he comes, the Lord will magnifie the law, make it great, though all the world have endeavoured to make nothing of it, or of no uſe at all a long time, when they ſhall againe judge by it, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118573:11"/>puniſh by it, and rule by it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, and more, the Lord will make it honourable alſo; they ſhall never ſet up traditions in the place thereof again. O Parliament, This God will do; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God will do this by you or not, and honour you herein or not, I do not know: you ſee it is my deſire, if it be his will, ye are witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and God alſo, that the work may be yours, who have done much of the work of the Lord in the Nation; that the honour here, and reward thereof hereafter, may be yours: and let me ſpeak freely to you thus, that if you will not do it, God in few yeers will not want them that will do it; upon whom, and whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, the bleſſings of God and the Nation will fall in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, who did that in their generation for them, was never done; it being then, and never untill then, fulfilled, that of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 10.19. <hi>I will provoke you to jealouſie by them that are not a people;</hi> that is, ſome heathens, vvhich none never yet did do, ſhould, as the Jews, nationally covenant with God in the covenant of <hi>Moſes;</hi> with which the Jews, as awaked, begin to thinke that people <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>-like ſteal away, or God gives away his birthright from him: the not doing whereof, delayes their call. Now what Nation in all the world is like to do this, as <hi>England!</hi> O that it might be offered them who would not refuſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth General.</head>
               <p>That to the Elders, Heads, and Judges, were other inferior ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate officers, to ſerve in the ſame rule, who have their authority from the Seriptures, and from God, as the reſt, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Firſt.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt have no other gods before me.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statutes.</head>
                  <p>DEut. 6.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118573:11"/>
                  <p>Chap. 10.20. <hi>Fear the Lord thy God; him ſhalt thou ſerve, and to him ſhalt thou cleave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 34.12. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, that thou make no cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the inhabitants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 15. <hi>Leſt thou and they go a whoring after their gods, and one call thee, and thou eat of their ſacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 11.6. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, that your hearts be not deceived to turn aſide to ſerve other Gods, and worſhip them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 8.19. <hi>If thou forget the Lord thy God, and walk after other Gods, and ſerve and worſhip them</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Deut. <hi>Thou ſhalt not go after other gods, the gods of the people round about you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 23.24. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to their gods, nor ſerve them, nor do after their works: thou ſhalt utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them, and quite break down their Images.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement for ſerving ſtrange Gods.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. On the earth.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 11.17. <hi>I will ſhut up heaven, and the land ſhall not give her fruit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.1. This was fulfilled in the dayes of <hi>Ahab.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. On the people or Nation.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 8.19. <hi>Ye ſhall periſh as the Nations god deſtroyed before your face.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. On particular perſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.3. Thoſe joyned to Baal-peor — <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. were hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the head againſt the Sun, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.3.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 22.20. <hi>He that ſacrificeth to any god ſave to the Lord alone, he ſhall be utterly deſtroyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 17.2. <hi>If a man or woman have tranſgreſſed the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and hath ſerved other Gods, and worſhipped them, either the Sun, or Moon, or any of the hoaſt of beaven, which I have not commanded thee,</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>If it be told thee</hi> (that is, the judge) <hi>and thou haſt heard of it, and inquired diligently; and behold, if it be true, and the thing certaine that ſuch abomination is wrought in Iſrael,</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>thou ſhalt bring him or her forth to the gates — and ſtone them with ſtones until they dye — and ſo ſhalt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118573:12"/>thou put away evil from amongſt you.</hi> Note, ſo by the executing this ſentence, and not any other of thy own: then it abides with thee; for it was not the judges condemning, but the peoples execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gods command, <hi>Put away evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.12. Contains judgement on a City for idolatry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The inhabitants and cattel are to be ſmitten with the ſword.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſpoile thou ſhalt gather into the middeſt of the City, and burn both City and ſpoile,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There ſhall nought of the wicked thing cleave to thy hand.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Deut. 18.6. <hi>If thy brother, ſon, daughter, wife, or friend, intice thee ſecretly, ſaying. Let us go and ſerve other gods which thou haſt not known, nor thy fathers,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, hear, nor pity, nor ſpare, nor conceal him;</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>The people ſhall ſtone him with ſtones, that he dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Deut. 13.2. <hi>If a prophet or dreamer give a ſigne or won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and it comes to paſs, and he ſay, Let us go after other gods thou haſt not known (it is to try thee) thou ſhalt not hear him; he ſhall be put to death.</hi> Deut. 18.20. <hi>If a Prophet preſumes to ſpeak in my name, that I have not ſpoken, or ſpeaks in the name of another god, he ſhall dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">VII. <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.13. <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.14. was ſtoned for and under the pretence of blaſphemy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Rules to be obſerved on the judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That God required the execution thereof onely of thoſe that had tranſgreſſed the covenant (which <hi>Moſes</hi> renewed oft) as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that ſtatute, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.2. who were to ſuffer the ſentence of the law, and none elſe; and ſo in moſt other eaſes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though thoſe were hanged joyned to Baal-peor, were hanged after ſtrangled, contrary to our cuſtome; and was the moſt ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous death, for joyning themſelves to Baal-peor or <hi>Priapus,</hi> that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnious idol.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord being the Lord of life, is not left to any to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the life of any but as God hath appointed; which for idolatry is generally ſtoning by the hands of all the people.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is obſerved by ſome, that when it is ſaid, <hi>His blood be on him,</hi> then ſtoning is meant; or otherwiſe when the death is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118573:12"/>then ſtrangling: but uſually, though the death be not ſet down in one place, it is in another.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In ſtoning, the people were to ſhew their hatred of the evil committed, that they and theirs might be free of the curſe and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned againſt them for the ſame; one man not being able to do the ſame, by that or any other way of putting to death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Jezebel</hi> and the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> ſlaine, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.22. and 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Ahazia</hi> ſends to <hi>Baal-zebub,</hi> and dyeth, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> ſlaine praiſing his gods, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.4, 5 30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.2. The Moabites called the people to the ſacrifices of their gods, and the people did eat, and bowed down to their gods; in which (<hi>verſ.</hi> 3.) they were ſaid to be joyned to Baal-peor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 17.7. <hi>They ſhall no more offer their ſacrifices to devils, after whom they have gone a whoring.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Verſe 9. <hi>Shall be cut off from among the people.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The command binds affirmatively,</hi> Thou ſhalt have me to thy God.</head>
                  <p>Now the way of Gods calling a people, and becoming a God to them nationally, is by giving them laws, and they taking them from him, and profeſſing ſubjection to them, as to their Gods commands whom they ought to ſerve.</p>
                  <p>To the keeping whereof, God adds by promiſe many bleſſings; as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 19.11. <hi>In keeping thereof is great reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the breach whereof, are added many curſes of body, ſoul, goods, name, family, earth, and heaven; all are ſhut up to men for it.</p>
                  <p>The which giving of laws royally to his people, is the only work and prerogative royal of God; and therefore is the law moral cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Royal law,</hi> Jam. 2.8. and thus the Scripture ſaith, <hi>There is hut one law-giver, who is able to ſave and deſtroy: who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi> Jam. 4.12.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118573:13"/>
                  <p>And hence are all laws of heathens ſaid to be no laws, and they <hi>without law;</hi> and all the ordinances, and the corrupt expoſitions of the law, made by ancient expoſitors, and received by their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren among the Jews, called <hi>traditions;</hi> and they were ſuch as <hi>made voide the law</hi> among them that had it. In which it appears, there is no law but Gods, nor no true law-maker but God; law, government, and judgement, among Gods people eſpecially, being his.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, As we muſt not have another God, ſo we muſt not have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laws then Gods: God will not govern by any other then his own laws.</p>
                  <p>Behold, I pray, by mens deelining Gods laws, what laws have been brought out ſince the reforming times; as in the 6 Articles in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. time, the book of Sports, and many laws ſince repealed. What is become of the Judges, Juſtices, and men, made and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe laws ſo contrary to the Lord and his law?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> brings in wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. ſaying, <hi>By me kings raigne, and the princes</hi> (that is, thoſe of the ſupreme councel) <hi>do deſcribe Juſtice</hi> (that is, to thoſe judges conſult with them about difficult caſes, without whom the difficult caſes would as well be hid to them as others.) Now if juſtice be ſo hard a thing to be executed by men who not only have the law, but uſe the law, and the help thereof to do juſtice, by that, without wiſdom or Chriſts help they cannot deſcribe it; how ſhall thoſe deſcribe it, that uſe not the law to help them, which ought to be their help; and ſo tempt God not to help them extraordinarily, for not uſing the ordinary help of God? And that he ſpeaks here of the great councel, is clear, they being next to the king; and then he ſpeaks of the ordinary Juges in the verſe following, to whom juſtice was to be deſcribed: which is ſignificant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet down, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.11.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 35.6. ſome there are contend to maintaine the law and cuſtomes we have in this Nation received from our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe the Rechabites ſtuck ſo cloſe to theirs. To which I anſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Rechabites were ſubject to the judicial law, as the other Jews were.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe traditions of theirs were not forbid nor commanded of God, that the magiſtrate could not forbid the doing what they did.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118573:13"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Nor were there any judiciary proceedings againſt ſuch as ſhould not have obſerved thoſe traditions, they being indifferent things only; it had been no ſin to them if they had drunk wine, or dwelt in houſes, or planted fields with ſeed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. So that theſe not ſtanding in competition with the law of God, they were not diſabled from obſerving one, and doing the other alſo.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The father of a family may ingage his ſons and ſervants to ſuch-like duties, as depending immediately on his rule; but it may be unlawful to a Magiſtrate to impoſe the like ordinances on a whole Nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Second.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statutes againſt idolatry.</head>
                  <p>HAbac. 2.18. <hi>The idol is a teacher of lyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.16, 17 18. Is forbid any graven image or ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of any figure or likeneſs of male or female, of beaſt, fowl, creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thing or fiſh. Sun Moon. or hoaſt of heaven.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 20.23. <hi>Ye ſhall not make with me gods of ſilver, nor ſhall ye make unto you gods of gold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 26.1. <hi>Ye ſhall make no idols nor graven images, nor rear up any ſtanding image, nor ſhall ye ſet up any image of ſtone to bow down.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 34.17. <hi>Ye ſhall make no molten gods,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 19.4. <hi>Turn ye not to idols, nor make to your ſelves molten Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dout. 4.23. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves loſt ye forget the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord which he made with you and make you a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image or the likeneſs of any thing which the Lord thy God hath for bidden thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 18.21. <hi>Thy ſeed ſhall not paſs the fire to</hi> Moloch.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118573:14"/>
                  <head>Judgements on Idolatry.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. On the Nation or people.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 9.12. <hi>They have made them a molten calf.</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>let me alone, that I may deſtroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven,</hi> Exod. 32.27.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 4.16. <hi>If ye corrupt your ſelves, and make a graven i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or likeneſs of any thing,</hi> Verſ. 26. <hi>I call heaven and earth to witneſs, ye ſhall ſoon utterly periſh.</hi> Verſ. 27. <hi>ye ſhall be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered among the nations,</hi> Verſ. 28. <hi>and ſerve gods of wood and ſtone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. On a perſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.4. Man or woman worſhipping the Sun Moon, or hoſt of heaven, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. was to be brought to the gates, and ſtoned to death.</p>
                  <p>Lev. 20.2. <hi>If an Iſraelite or ſtranger,</hi> who ever he be, <hi>giveth any of his ſeed to Moloch he ſhall ſurely dye:</hi> the people of the land (not of the City only) <hi>ſhall ſtone him with ſtones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note. Verſ. 4. <hi>If the people of the land any way hide their eyes from that man and kill him not:</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Then will I ſet my face againſt that man and his family, and will cut him off, and all that go a whoring after him: I will ſet my face againſt that ſoul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Deut. 27.15. <hi>Curſed is that man that puts any graven or molten image in a ſecret place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. On the idols.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 7.5. <hi>Deſtroy their altars, and break down their images: their groves ſhall ye cut down, and burn their graven images with fire.</hi> Numb. 33.52. <hi>ye ſhall deſtroy all their pictures and molten images, and pluck down their high places.</hi> Numb. 32.52. <hi>and quite pluck down all their high places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. Judgement is on the places of idol-worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 12.2. <hi>Ye ſhall utterly deſtroy all the places wherein the nations ye ſhall poſſeſs ſerved their gods, upon the high mountains and hills, and under every green tree.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 3. <hi>Ye ſhall overthrow their altars, break their pillars, and burn their groves with fire: ye ſhall throw down the graven images of their gods,</hi> Judg. 6.25. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 32. 2 Chron. 23.17.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118573:14"/>
                  <p n="6">VI. Judgements is one the names of the falſe gods.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 7.25. <hi>Ye ſhall deſtroy the names of them out of that place,</hi> Zech. 13.2. the ſame ſhall be done in time to come.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. Judgement is on the idols of gold and ſilver.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 7.25. <hi>The graven images of their gods ſhall ye burn with fire. Then ſhalt not deſire the ſilver or gold that is on them, nor take it to thee, leſt thou be ſnared therein: for it is an abomination to the Lord thy God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 26. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bring in an abomination into thy houſe, leſt thou be an accurſed thing like it; but ſhalt utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt it and abhor it; for it is an accurſed thing,</hi> Vide Joſhua 6.18, and Chapter 7.1, 15, 21. to the end of the Chapter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obſervations.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That metals were to be melted with fire; ſtone, glaſs, and ſuch-like fragil things, were to be broken with the hammer to powder.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What work hath God to do yet for us, were we once joyned by covenant to the Lord! names of moneths, dayes of the week, and thoſe places we call Churches, Altars; the names of idols, falſe gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are daily and hourely in our mouths, as in our ſwearing by the Maſs.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It defiles a land.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How this nation by worſhipping of idols in the time of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath profaned that Scripture is the covenant, is clear; and in regard he is a jealous God, he is no leſs jealous of our apoſtatizing, then of our fathers; eſpecially ſeeing we have done hitherto the work of the Lord negligently, not making our covenant in a right way; taking him to be our God, but not in his laws to judge and rule over us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He viſiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children, you may ſee, without a ſpeedy covenanting with God according to his will, what provocation there remaines: for God, whoſe hand is yet ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to deſtroy us, we having been as idolatrous, ſuperſtitious, and profane a people as any in the world: O England, remember the bloodſhed for the idol of the Maſs, and its worſhip, and that by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118573:15"/>Statutes and Acts of Parliament; together with the other ſix bloody Articles made by King and Parliament in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It may be ſaid, as thoſe in <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.9. <hi>Who can tell whether the Lord will turn and repent?</hi> ſo, if the King had made this covenant, and ſet up this law, this had been the way for to have reſtored him: but it was hid from his eyes. I beſeech you, O ye Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> be admoniſhed; do this great thing, that the Lord lay not you aſide alſo: and if ye hinder herein, ſee what a command God hath given againſt all hinderances, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.14. <hi>Caſt ye up, caſt ye up; prepare the way; take up the ſtumbling-block out of the way of my people.</hi> God hath of late taken up many that were ſtumbling-b ocks among your ſelves ſince ye ſate, and will ſpare none that indeed is ſo this day to his peoples freedom and deliverance.</p>
                  <p>And that the judicial law ought to be ſet up among us as well as the Jews, clearly was ſignified in this, that the law was to be one as well to the ſtranger, as to thoſe home-born, which ſhould not have been, if God had intended it only to have been a law to Jews, and nor the Gentiles alſo; there being the ſame ground for equity juſtice, and for fellowſhip with God, with one, as with the other; with God there being no reſpect of perſons, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.10.22. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.29, 33 31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16. &amp; 5.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Objections made by Sir <hi>H. V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Object. 1. <hi>To reſtore the rule of the law, is to Judaize.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. To rule by our own law, is to heathenize.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Having Gods law, and yet to rule by that, is much worſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We now Judaize, by making void the law of God by our Traditions.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To Judaize is properly to continue in Gods worſhip ſome ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony Chriſt by his death hath put an end unto.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The law judicial hath nothing ceremonial in it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt put not an end to it, but eſtabliſhed it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Law was not made for the Jew only, but All, and ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely to be made for tranſgreſſors thereof of all Nations, 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1, 9, 10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Object. <hi>We look for a better kinde of rule from Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118573:15"/>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Reſp.</hi> As there ſhall never be another Goſpel, ſo ſhall there never be another law; God having ſhut up all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As there cannot be a Goſpel more full of grace, ſo nor can there be a law more full of juſtice and righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How can we expect that from God, which neither by himſelf, his Son nor Prophets, in all the book of God, was never promiſed, no not by one word?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If it were ſuppoſed a better law for goverment of the republike might be given, as can never be,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Quere,</hi> 1. Whether we might receive it without warrant expreſly given by God, whiles we have that of Gods, which he gave himſelf.</item>
                        <item>2. If be that gave it be not accurſed, as he that ſhould give another Goſpel, 1 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1, 9.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whether it be not exceedingly to derogate from God, to eſteem of any rule like or above his.</p>
                  <p>Its objected by ſome <hi>That the Jews had ſeveral Synedries,</hi> viz. the ſevnty, and twenty three.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> From <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. God will reſtore councellors as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning not councels; that is, but one; and the Synedrie is but one, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. and not Synedries: ſo that the Jews in ſetting up more then one Synedrie, did a poſtatize from the rule.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Third.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord the God in vaine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>DEut. 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt ſwear by his name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 19.12. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſwear by my name falſly, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane the name of thy God,</hi> Jer. 5.7. <hi>thy children ſwear by them are no gods.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118573:16"/>
                  <head>Judgements.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. (<hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. verſ. 2.3.) on a land,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For oaths the land mourneth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. On a family, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29. <hi>He that blaſphemed God, his houſe ſhall be deſtroyed, and himſelf cut in pieces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Zech. 5.4. <hi>The flying roul entred into the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly by my name, and it ſhall remaine in the midſt of his houſe, and it ſhall conſume it, with the timber thereof, and the ſtones thereof.</hi> Jezabel ſwore by her gods, and is eaten by dogs, and her familly cut off, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. On a perſon.</p>
                  <p>Levit. 24.15. <hi>Whoever curſeth his God, and he blaſphemeth the name of God, ſhall ſurely dye, as well the ſtranger, as he that is born in the land: all the Congregation ſhall ſtone him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.11. The ſon of an Iſraelitiſh woman blaſphemed the name of God, and curſed; and they brought him to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put him in ward, until the minde of the Lord were known.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 14. He is brought out of the Camp, and ſtoned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Illuſtr. Davids</hi> child dyed, becauſe he made the enemy blaſpheme, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.31. <hi>Regard not them that have familiar ſpirits, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeek after wizards to be defiled by them. I am the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 26. <hi>Ye ſhall not uſe inchantments, nor obſerve times.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 18.10. <hi>There ſhall not be found amongſt you any that uſeth divination, or any obſerver of times, or an enchanter, or a witch, or a charmer, or a conſulter with familiar ſpirits, a wiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, or a Necromancer: all theſe are an abomination before the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgements.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a witch to live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 20.27. <hi>A man or woman that hath a familiar ſpirit, or is a wizard, ſhall ſurely be put to death: they ſhall ſtone them with ſtones; their blood ſhall be upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 6. <hi>The ſoul that turneth after ſuch as have familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118573:16"/>and after wizards, to go a whoring after them, I will even ſet my face againſt that ſoul, and will cut him off from among his people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> God will cut him off by ſome judgement: this was not to be done by the Magiſtrate, but left to God himſelf, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.31. in <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 20.22. <hi>Ye ſhall keep all my Statutes and my judgements, to do them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 23. <hi>Ye ſhall not walk in the manners of the Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 18.3. <hi>After the doings of the land of Egypt ſhall ye not do; after the doings of the land of Canaan where I bring you ſhall ye not do, neither ſhall ye walk in their ordinances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 4. <hi>Ye ſhall do my judgements, and keep mine ordinances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 19.27. <hi>Thou ſhalt not round the corners of thy head, nor war the corners of thy beard, nor make cuttings in thy fleſh for the dead nor print any markes on you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 18.9. <hi>Ye ſhall not do after the abominations of the heathen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſervation.</hi> The Lord bindes the people that have his Statutes, to make uſe of his, and not any other ordinances, laws, or manners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Numb. 15.30, 31. <hi>The ſoul that doth ought preſumptuouſly, whether he be born in the land, or a ſtranger, the ſame reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord, and that ſoul ſhall be cut off from among his people, becauſe he hath deſpiſed the word of the Lord, and hath broken his commandment: that ſoul ſhall utterly be cut off; his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be upon him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O ye Princes and Judges of the people, if men judge by other judgements then Gods, and have Gods judgements by them, to judge by; judge ye if they do not preſumptuouſly what they do, in ſo doing, that they were to dye for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> The Jews mixed firſt heatheniſh cuſtomes in ſacrifices, in the law: the Jews believers, in the time of the Goſpel mixed Jewiſh rites and the Goſpel-adminſtrations together; the heathens their rites and the Goſpel: we now, Antichriſtian ſuperſtitions, and the way of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118573:17"/>Gods worſhip, in the Goſpel, whoſe manners and cuſtoms we ought to abſtaine from, as the Jews from the heathens, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9.10, 11. &amp; 18.4.8. They being a like abomination before the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The excellency of ſetting up of the commands and ſtatutes, and the government of God by making a covenant with God doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear moſt eminently in the national preſervation of the Jews from the witchcraft of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who cryeth out to <hi>Balack,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>There is no divination againſt Iſrael, nor enchantment againſt Jacob,</hi> Numb. 23.23. and the reaſon is, the Lord is his God (by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant) and he is with him: and <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>How ſhall I curſe whom God hath not curſed?</hi> Chap. 24.9. <hi>Bleſſed is he that bleſſeth thee, and curſed is he that curſeth thee:</hi> which ſhews, had not God been his God, witchcrafts, inchantments, and curſes, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Balaam</hi> farther ſaith, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.9. <hi>The people ſhall dwell alone, and not be reckoned among the Nations.</hi> When a people make a covenant with God, they are then a people, which before were not. O that in <hi>England</hi> might be fulfilled that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They ſhall dwell alone, being a peculiar people to God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Not reckoned among the Nations, but ſeparated from them in their laws, goverment, worſhip of God <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God bleſſing them, when other nations are accurſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Then when we covenant rightly into the Lord, he ſets his name upon us, and we called the people of God, and not before. And to theſe and not others, is <hi>the name of God a ſtrong tower; the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous fly unto it, and are ſafe:</hi> they coming unto the Lord as to their God and refuge; God being their refuge and hiding place; which he is not to any other nation but theſe.</p>
                  <p>Treaſon, called <hi>crimen laeſae majeſtatis,</hi> againſt God, is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe three commands: and many traitors there are amongſt us, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Concerning the Treatiſe of the Sabbath.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. From <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> the authority was by tradition, and the firſt-born was prieſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By tradition Chriſt was diſcovered in the promiſe to <hi>Adam</hi> to many nations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The authority was from Scripture, in the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and other judicial precepts.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118573:17"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Under it, the traditional authority ceaſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The prieſthood of the firſt-born ceaſed, and was given <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Now ſacrifices of other were offered to devils.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This was only for the ſeventh-day-Sabbath.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. This Sabbath was a part of, and ſign to the firſt covenant.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Chriſt comming, was the Angel of, and Mediator to a better covenant.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſign whereof is the firſt-day-Sabbath.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As this is of the ſecond covenant, ſo it cannot be mixt with the firſt; but are to be reſerved diſtinct, and not confounded: for as the two covenants cannot be one, ſo nor can the Sabbaths.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Hence then to force obedience of one on all, is to deſtroy the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To force the world to obſerve the firſt-day-Sabbath, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the uſe of the day, and make void the grace of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In deſtroying any of the Sabbaths, is to deſtroy the covenant, and to take away the very ſigne thereof; as at this day it is done by and amongſt us.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Fourth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Remember the Sabbath day, to keep it holy.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>EXod. 23.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt reſt the ſeventh day, that thy Ox and Aſs may reſt; that the ſon of thy handmaid and ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be refreſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Numb. 28.25. Jer. 17.21. <hi>Carry no burden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 23.3. <hi>It is the Sabbath of the Lord in all their dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 16.29. <hi>Let no man go out of his place on the Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 26. <hi>Ye ſhall finde no manna thereon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 31.16. <hi>The children of Iſrael ſhall keep the Sabbath, to obſerve the Sabbath throughout their generations, for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi>
                     <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118573:18"/>continue untill Chriſt came, and carnal ceremonies were put to an end, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. God in <hi>Horeb</hi> makes a covenant with all the people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2, 3. and in <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.16. <hi>The children of Iſrael ſhall keep the Sabbath, to obſerve the Sabbath throughout all their congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for a perpetual covenant: it is a ſigne between me and the children of Iſrael for ever,</hi> Exod. 34.27.</p>
                  <p>Objected, <hi>This ſeems to hold out three covenants; and the Scripture holds out but two.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That <hi>Abraham</hi> had, is the ſame with ours; and hence is <hi>Abraham</hi> called <hi>the father of the faithful:</hi> onely the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations thereof differs now, from what it had then.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This covenant of the Law continuing, the ſigne thereof muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo continue, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.20. <hi>My Sabbath,</hi> as diſtinct from the Lords day.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Scriptures call after Chriſts reſurrection the ſeventh-dayes-Sabbath Sabbath, as well as the firſt, if rightly tranſlated.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles met with the Jews, and taught them that day uſually.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. No Scripture ſhews the aboliſhing thereof.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It is neceſſary thoſe under that covenant ſhould have a day and time to ſerve God in, as thoſe under the new.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Sabbath of the new muſt not be to thoſe under the old covenant, nor the Sabbath of the old to thoſe under the new, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Men put not new wine into old bottles, nor peece an old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with a new peece of cloth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. In the eſtate of the Church, all things are become new: but then it is only with ſuch as are of the Church: with others not of the Church, they are ſo under the old covenant, as if there had never been any new. Mark, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>what the law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the law,</hi> Rom. 3.13. ſo that thoſe under the Law are commanded to work ſix dayes, and reſt the ſeventh only.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Thus not an iota or tittle of the law periſheth: the morality of the ſeventh-day-Sabbath is continued; and yet no Judaizing in the thing: for this was no part of the ceremonial law; the ground of the ſeventh day being from the creation; but of the ceremonies, from the redemption of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Thus Chriſt deſtroyes not the law, but eſtabliſheth it; Jeſus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118573:18"/>Chriſt not taking unbelievers from being under the law, in which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate they were, and ſubjection thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. God will judge them by the law, that are under the law. Now the law requires them that are under it, to keep the ſeventh day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. and thoſe that are riſen with Chriſt, and marryed to him, are under the Goſpel, and Goſpel-day: this truth ſhines forth clearly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3, 4. where untill the woman is married to Chriſt, ſhee is under her firſt husband <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. The one hath a reſt with God, and beaſt, and creatures, by <hi>Moſes;</hi> the other hath a reſt with God, and Chriſt, and angels: ſouls of juſt men made perfect on mount <hi>Sion. Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note. Moſes</hi> and Chriſt are two, and do not deſtroy each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Chriſt onely perfects <hi>Moſes:</hi> the covenants are two, the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths two, the ſtates two; one of the world, the other of the Church; one under the law, the other under the Goſpel: which eſtates are not to be confounded or made one.</p>
                  <p>Hence, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Let no man judge you in reſpect of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Keeping the ſeventh day Sabbath while unbelievers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Being received by the Church, and now obſerve the firſt, and work on the ſeventh, whereas before, he wrought on the firſt, and ſanctified the ſeventh; juſtly brings men to be judged and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſo doing among men not knowing the truth, and the will of God therein.</p>
                  <p>A ſtrange confuſion in the world for ſome time there was, if we may believe <hi>Socrates;</hi> who ſaith, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> obſerved onely the firſt day Sabbath, and all other Churches the ſeventh. See into what diviſion the loſs of truth had brought the then world into; and ever ſince, in this darkneſs aroſe out of the bottomleſs-pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.3. hath the world been ſhut up.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that is under the law-day Sabbath, is to be puniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its law, if he obſerve it not; and he that is under the Goſpel-Sabbath, is to be proceeded againſt according to the way of the Goſpel, by thoſe ſeveral powers ſet up of God in them.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>God requires but one day of ſeven; this is two.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> One day is but obſerved: for thoſe obſerve the firſt, are not bound to obſerve the ſeventh; and thoſe bound to obſerve the ſeventh, are not bound to obſerve the firſt.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118573:19"/>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Some would then be buying, ſelling, merchandizing on both dayes, and no day obſerved: which would be very groſs confuſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> This confuſion in the Apoſtles dayes, if you call it ſo: and the Apoſtle never tearmed it ſuch at all, but ſaith, <hi>Let no man judge you</hi> (much more let no man condemne you) <hi>in reſpect of Sabbath dayes,</hi> Col. 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By this means the Apoſtles gathered the Jews and Judaizing Gentiles, teaching in the Synagogues on the ſeventh, and after in the Churches on the firſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By this, as the Jews held a preparation to their Sabbath, ſo now is the ſeventh dayes Sabbath a preparation to the firſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There is no ſin, where is no law, <hi>Moſes</hi> gave no command to thoſe under the law, to obſerve the firſt day: Chriſt gave no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to thoſe under grace, to obſerve the ſeventh day Sabbath.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Anrichriſt could never have made the Church and the world one, but by deſtroying thoſe ordinances that ſeparated them; and making them one in Church-ordinances, it was eaſie to perſwade the world to be one with the Church, but not the Church with the world.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. is, <hi>If the law-eſtate can be reſtored and not the ſeventh dayes Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether men, untill they are Evangelically called thence, are not of and under that eſtate, in reſpect of their viſible eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>The Apoſtles gathered many from Paganiſme, and never were under the law at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> The legal external adminiſtration was in a manner abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe were gathered, were under it, ſpiritually and inwardly, before they were gathered.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If God effectually called them to be under the ſecond, the firſt was waxen old to them then only, and not before.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Who ſhall be Miniſters of this adminiſtration, ſeeing</hi> Aarons <hi>prieſthood dyeth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp. Aaron</hi> was not the Miniſter of this; this was miniſtred in the Synagogues: <hi>Aaron</hi> miniſtred in the temple onely.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Scribes or Lawyers, which were not Levites or Prieſts, they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118573:19"/>read the law in Synagogues, and are ſaid to <hi>ſit in Moſes</hi> (not Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons) <hi>chaire, Mat.</hi> 23.2, 3.</p>
                  <p>In the Synagogue it was common to read or teach, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.16, 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. The ruler of the Synagogue I take to be none elſe but one deſigned in eſpecial to take care of the well-ordering of all things to be done therein.</p>
                  <p>In the word is no prieſthood after this adminiſtration, but a ſcribe, a writer of the law, that knew how to read it well. Hence the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are called a Kingdome of Prieſts, every one being to be a law-prieſt, for expounding the judicial law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>What confuſion would this bring forth in families!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Is there more amongſt us then was among Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles at the firſt erecting of Churches?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Did not Chriſt foretell as much, when he ſaid there ſhould in one houſe be three againſt two, and two againſt three? <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.52.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Doth not the Apoſtle ſay the ſervant then to the heathen was <hi>the Lords freeman?</hi> 1 Cor. 7. See how God plagued <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for keeping his people from ſerving him.</p>
                  <p>Object. Rev. 18.4. <hi>God calls his people out of Babel, or Rome, the falſe Church onely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> This is the firſt ſtep from her, to ſeparate the world and Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We are not to come out of Babels Church-practice onely, but her ſtate-practices alſo; not in duties of the Goſpel only, but the law alſo. A people in civil ſociety cannot be without the law; as in the Church-ſociety they cannot be without the Goſpel, and be with and under God therein.</p>
                  <p>The firſt-day-Sabbath is of the covenant of grace; the ſeventh, of works. <hi>Moſes</hi> is taught the ſeventh, Chriſt the firſt: natural men obſerve one, believers the other; yet both ſanctified, and Sabbaths, and to be kept holy.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>This would be exceeding loſs to the Nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Never man did loſe by ſerving God, but gaine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The godly man muſt ſell all, If he will be a Chriſtian, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf, and be dead to all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> The heathens ſet apart ſome time to ſerve their Gods of wood and ſtone in, though they had no warrant to do the ſame:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118573:20"/>ſhall not thoſe are the people of God much more have ſome day to ſerve him in? and what day, but that God in the laws inſtituted, from which before the <hi>Son hath made them free,</hi> they are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from what ſervice the law requires, nor what penalty the law impoſeth on them for diſobedience: apply <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p>Hear what the law ſaith to thoſe under the law, <hi>James</hi> 2.10. <hi>Whoſoever keepeth the whole law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> Rom. 3.19. <hi>that every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may become guilty before God.</hi> Gal. 3.10. <hi>Curſed be every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the law, to do them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> This ſeems to me, that men under the law are ſtrictly bound to the obſervation of the ſeventh-day-Sabbath: of which number all unbelievers are, who are bound to ſerve God for the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts and mercies, though they know not Chriſt, but are in the ſtate of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> The Lords-day-Sabbath is only to be obſerved in the Church, by men made free by Chriſt from the law, curſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation thereof. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. <hi>There remaineth a Sabbatiſme to the people of God;</hi> called <hi>another day,</hi> verſ. 8. from the 7. Note <hi>verſe</hi> 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>This is of great concernment to be inquired into, that whiles we ſtrive to build up what we ſhould not, we pull down what we ought not. I hope you would not for a world make a law to make void the law of God.</p>
                  <p>The Sabbath gave way to circumciſion, though it were not of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is, <hi>Moſes</hi> law. <hi>John</hi> 7.22, 23. that the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning circumciſion might not be broken.</p>
                  <p>It is very remarkable, that in all the conflicts the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees had with Chriſt about the Sabbath, he never ſpake of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it, nor condemned the right obſervance of it; though the Jews were more oft offended at Chriſt for this, then any thing; he curing more on that day, then any, becauſe looked on by the Lord as the work of the day; and they the more troubled at it, becauſe done thereon, which they judged to be a profanation thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> As the law was given by the found of Trumpet, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of the Synagogues were to be called by trumpet, and not by bells, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.16. which minded them of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118573:20"/>of the law, and the covenant then made the believers by riſing of the Sun, that is, the time and call of them for their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sabbath dayes journey,</hi> ſome underſtand one ſome to be two miles; which was no leſs to be obſerved under the Goſpel, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law-day-Sabbath. <hi>Joſhua</hi> 3.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures rightly expounded, will clear this Antichriſtian darkneſs. O take the vaile from our eyes and hearts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.1. The Sabbath being end, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. Early in the morn, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and the firſt of Sabbaths; it being the firſt of the Lords-day-Sabbath, or the firſt of the two Sabbaths; the Lords day being the firſt, the ſeventh day the laſt of the week, according to the Scripture, <hi>The firſt ſhall be laſt, and laſt firſt.</hi> And for the ceremonial Sabbath, they are no more called Sabbaths, but the ſeventh and firſt day are called Sabbaths alway in the word.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures ſpeaking of the Lords-day-Sabbath, miſinterpreted for the firſt day of the week, and calls the ſeventh day a Sabbath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, are theſe: <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</p>
                  <p>That the Scriptures are miſinterpreted when read <hi>the firſt day of the week,</hi> is clear; for when God ſpeaks of the firſt day of the week, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.9. he ſaith <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the ſingular; no <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the plural; and thus the Phariſees, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.12. faſted <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. After Chriſt, the Law-day-Sabbath was obſerved by the Jews, men under the Law, among whom the Apoſtles taught, and never in one word reproved them. <hi>Acts</hi> 18 2. <hi>Paul, as his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was, went into the Synagogue to the Jews, and three Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath dayes reaſoned out of the Scriptures with them.</hi> Note, <hi>his manner was:</hi> and thus in many other Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lords-day-Sabbath was obſerved among believers, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. <hi>On the firſt,</hi> or one of the Sabbaths, <hi>when the Diſciples came together to bread bread</hi> Paul <hi>preached to them,</hi> &amp;c. and that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. <hi>On every firſt of Sabbaths</hi> (a command to the Church of <hi>Corinth) every one of you lay by him in ſtore as God hath proſpered him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Having ſhewed you, that both the firſt and the ſeventh day,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118573:21"/>that under the covenant of the law, and that under the covenant of grace; <hi>Moſes</hi> Sabbath day, and Chriſts, conjunctly are called Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and ſo of divine authority alike; onely one is a command to men under the law, the other to men under grace: now I ſhall ſhew you how they are diſtinctly called Sabbaths.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.4. He ſpeaks of the ſeventh dayes reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. In this againe of <hi>an other</hi> reſt, which is a dayes reſt, as the ſeventh day was, is clear, from <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. and the 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 9. This other day is called <hi>Sabbatiſmos,</hi> a ſabbatiſme; which is proper onely to the Church or people of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. This Sabbath-reſt men muſt ſtrive to enter into; in the other, all men are compelled: in this, none but believers in the Kingdome of God injoy, into which men are bid to ſtrive to enter.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Here they are ſaid to enter into this ſabbatiſme, which is proper to the ſtate of heaven to be entred into.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Believers in Chriſt are ſaid to enter into, or be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the law to Chriſt; or one in law, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.21.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.5. <hi>Chriſt is ſaid to be</hi> Lord of the Sabbath: <hi>and in what was he ſo, but in putting an end to it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> That Scripture ſaith not ſo, and is contrary to many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scriptures, where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>A tittle of the law ſhall not periſh:</hi> and the Scripture is falſly rendered, the word is; <hi>The Lord is Son of man, and of the Sabbath;</hi> becauſe made of woman, and made under the law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="commandment">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118573:21"/>
               <head>Command the Fifth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Honour thy father and thy mother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>LEvit. 19.3. <hi>Ye ſhall fear every man his father and mother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 32. <hi>Ye ſhall riſe up before the hoary head, and honor the face of the old man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 7.10. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.6. Iſaac ſubmitteth to his father to dye. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.51. and thus Jeſus Chriſt: the Rechabites obedience, <hi>Jer.</hi> 35. and Gods bleſſing them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgements.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25, 26. <hi>Noah</hi> curſeth <hi>Cham</hi> with bondage, and bleſſeth <hi>Japhet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 27.16. <hi>Curſed be he ſetteth lightly by his father or mother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 20.9. <hi>Every one that curſeth his father or mother, ſhall ſurely be put to death; his blood ſhall be upon him,</hi> Exod. 21.17.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.15. <hi>He that ſmiteth his father or mother, ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be put to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Numb. 12.14. <hi>If her father had ſpit in her face, ſhould ſhe not have been aſhamed ſeven dayes?</hi> which was a thing of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.9. and it may be either for diſobeying, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 7.10. The Goſpel confirms it; <hi>Who curſeth father or mother, let him dye the death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prov. 30.17. <hi>The eye that mocketh at his father, and deſpiſeth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley ſhall pick it out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 4.9. <hi>Forget not the things thine eyes have ſeen.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118573:22"/>teach them thy ſons, and thy ſons ſons:</hi> Verſ. 10. <hi>Eſpecially the day thou ſtoodeſt before the Lord in Horeb:</hi> Verſ. 13. <hi>and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to you his covenant which he commanded you to performe, even the ten commandments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 6.7. <hi>Thou ſhalt teach them diligently thy children, and ſhalt talk of them when thon ſitteſt in thy houſe, when thou walkeſt by the way, when thou lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt up.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 21.18. <hi>If a man have a ſtubborn and a rebellious ſon that will not obey the voice of his father or his mother, and that when they have chaſtened him, he will not hearken unto them;</hi> Verſ. 19. <hi>Then ſhall his father and mother lay hold of him, and bring him out to the Elders of his City and the gate of his place:</hi> Verſ. 20. <hi>They ſhall ſay to the Elders of his City, This our ſon is ſtubborn and rebellious, and will not hear our voice: he is a drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and a glutton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 21. <hi>All the men of his City ſhall ſtone him with ſtones that he dye: ſo ſhalt thou put away evil from amongſt you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Why is ſo much rebellion againſt parents, is not becauſe the law of God is ſilent; this being executed, all <hi>England</hi> would hear and fear.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Is there another way, beſides this, to put away evil from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, appointed of God? Note, God ſaith, <hi>So ſhalt thou put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way evil,</hi> and no other way.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or is not the Law of God juſt, the judgement true and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it is not ſet up amongſt us? or will it ever be well with us or ours, until it be ſet up?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Parents marriage of their children, It was to be confined to ſuch as were in convenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 34.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take of their daughters to thy ſons, and their daughters go a whoring after their Gods, and make thy ſons go a whoring after their Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 7.3. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make marriages with thoſe nations God will deſtroy; thy daughter ſhalt thou not give his ſon, nor
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118573:22"/>his daughter ſhalt thou take to thy ſon.</hi> The reaſon whereof is rendred, <hi>verſ</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> As men under the law were not to match with thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were not under the law; ſo men under grace were not at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to match with any but ſuch as were in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Were we under the law, this would condemne all marriage with idolaters, more ſtrongly then the work of the law in us hath done. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.6. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.25. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. from 1. to <hi>verſe</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. See here the authority God hath given to men under the law, over their childrens marriage; they are ſaid to give and take: <hi>Eſau took a daughter of Canaan; Jacob obeyed his mother, and marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Labans daughter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.9. <hi>If a man betroth his maid-ſervant to his ſon, he ſhall deal with her after the manner of daughters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Betrothing was the fathers work, in which he gave his daughter, or took the daughter of ſome other to his ſon to wife.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Magiſtrate or Elders are not to approve of marriage made with any out of covenant.</p>
                  <p>It is to be conſidered, that God (under this word <hi>Father</hi>) doth comprehend the Magiſtrate; and obedience and honour hence due to him:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe all authority and rule was firſt in the father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It came from him to the one Judge <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. To Judges in every City, who had laws from God to judge the people by: in which adminiſtration only, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.12. the Lord God was ſaid to be their King. And now againe, when this law is the rule of judgement to the nation, then is the Lord Chriſt ſaid to raigne, which ſhall be a thouſand yeers; God having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all judgement and authority to the Son, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. and who would not ſtrive to ſet up Chriſts rule?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> As Judges were of God before Kings, ſo if Kings be put down, ye muſt return to Judges again; God ſetting up but theſe two wayes of rule, and God himſelf ruling in that of Judges, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſt: nor doth God rule by Judges as diſtinct from Kings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be ſet up as in the beginning, to rule by the laws of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The government came from Judges to Kings; in which the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118573:23"/>people were ſaid, in their asking for a King, to have <hi>committed great wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.17. yea, and God himſelf ſaid, herein they had rejected him, and not <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> that he ſhould not raigne over them. I beſeech you, what the government of Judges by the law God had ſet up was then to God, and this day is no leſs with him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. God had foretold of this by <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 17. and the thing oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned this, was conſiderable, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.3. which was <hi>Samuels</hi> age, and his ſons perverting Judgement, and taking bribes, and turning after lucre; yet <hi>Samuel, verſ.</hi> 6. is diſpleaſed at it, when they ſaid, <hi>Give us a King;</hi> to which God bids <hi>Samuel</hi> hearken, and do for them: under whom aroſe tribute, cuſtome, and imperious commands, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11. to the end of <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This rule of Kings, God in the Goſpel eſtabliſhed by <hi>Paul,</hi> 13.1. <hi>the powers that be,</hi> (even <hi>Nero's</hi> and his deputies) were ſaid to be <hi>ordained of God,</hi> in the Lords ſetting up of <hi>Saul:</hi> which fourth Monarchies rule was authoritative, untill the time God had ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it ſhould be <hi>taken out of the way,</hi> for the wickedneſs thereof, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. and the way how it ſhall be taken away, is ſet down, and by whom, even by the ſtone cut out of the mountaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands: he brake in peeces the iron, braſs, clay, ſilver, and gold, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44, 45. which puts an end to the fourth Monarchy, which ſhall have its end by Jeſus Chriſt. So that as the fourth Monarchy (or Roman) put down the law of God, Chriſt comes now to put down that in the rule, yea all the rule, authority, and power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. After all this, comes the <hi>ancient of dayes,</hi> which is not God, who is not of time nor dayes, but he comes by his law, and Judges and judgement, to ſit and judge againe; God having foretold he would <hi>reſtore Judges as at the firſt,</hi> Iſa. 1.26. to whom government ſhall be given of God, God having taken it from the Monarchy, that they may rule againe. And now as God is ſaid to give, ſo ſhall it be given by men unto them; in which God is alſo ſaid to give it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.27. and that their authority ſhall not be queſtioned, as <hi>Moſes</hi> once was, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who made thee a prince and Judge over us?</hi> the people making them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118573:23"/>
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. Judges are ſaid to be placed over the people, and are called gods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.6. The maſter was to bring the ſervant that would not go out free, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> unto the Gods, that is, unto the Judges.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 22.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the ruler of thy people.</hi> Pſal. 82.1. <hi>God ſtandeth in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Great is the honour ſet on Judges, they judging for and under God. I do not remember that it is ſaid of any Judges but theſe, nor any other kind of rulers. <hi>Nero</hi> was not a God in this ſence, though his authority were of God. The ſaying of Chriſt clears this, <hi>John</hi> 10.34. <hi>It is written in your law, I ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> verſ. 35. <hi>If he called them Gods to whom the word of God came,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that none are ſo called, but ſuch to whom the word of God came, that is, ſuch as by the words of God judged men, as in the place of God, being ſet up of God to judge thereby, that judgement may be the Lords.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. He that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> law was to dye, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12. this in the judgement on <hi>Core, Numb.</hi> 16.11. they are ſaid to be gathered together againſt the Lord, queſtioning <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom God had ſet up; and his government, which God had given as a law to that people. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. they ſay of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he had made, not God, altogether a prince, and not a Judge over the people, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. for which, they and theirs were deſtroyed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Iſa. 38.1. <hi>Command thy houſe</hi> (or ſet it in order) <hi>for thou ſhalt dye.</hi> Note, that the law had a rule in it, what men, and how they were to diſpoſe of their goods and eſtates in a way of Juſtice, and not according to their luſts; according to which rule, they were to divide their eſtates among them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There was a dowry of virgins, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.16. fifty ſhekels, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.29.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The firſt-born, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.17. was to have a double portion of all his father had; and the reaſon added was not for any cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial cauſe, but that he was <hi>the beginning of his ſtrength.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118573:24"/>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 36.2. <hi>Moſes</hi> would not make any law in the caſe of <hi>Zelophehad,</hi> though he were as able as any living, but he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of God who ſhould inherit: and it was reſolved, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.8. <hi>If a man dye and have no ſon then ye ſhall cauſe his inheritance to paſs unto his daughters: if he have no daughter, ye ſhall give his inheritance to his brethren: if he have no brethren, ye ſhall give it to his fathers brethren: if his father have no brethren, ye ſhall give it to his kinſman is next unto him of his family; he ſhall poſſeſs it: and it ſhall be to the children of Iſrael a ſtatute.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> How contrary are the practices of this people and nation to Gods law!</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>In doing thus, we ſhould wrong the dead, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> In doing Gods will, ye can do no wrong.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe that do juſtice, do not do wrong. But thoſe do thus, do juſtice: <hi>ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The dead and living do wrong to themſelves and conſciences, and others alſo, in doing that is forbid by Gods law to be done by them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Many holds and cuſtoms neceſſarily by this law are to be changed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Many other laws do depend on this in civil contracts.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How would this quench ſtrife and diviſion among brethren, and prevent the ruine of many families, and eſtabliſh love, this being the righteous Judgement of God!</p>
                  <p n="7">7. How would this prevent that ſhame in the nation, where one (the eldeſt brother) hath all, and is a prince; and the reſt all poor, and he onely lords it over all the reſt!</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Theſe holds are eſtabliſhed by law and cuſtome, and may not be changed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> If a law of man be contrary to the law of God, it is no law, but a tradition: and men are bound to alter it, when they know Gods mind to be to the contrary in the caſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If a man keeps from him that hath right to a poſſeſſion, his poſſeſſion, it is no wrong to take it from him, and give it to whom it juſtly pertains, but an act of Juſtice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.11. <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Luk. 12.13. <hi>And one of the company ſaid unto him, Maſter,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118573:24"/>ſpeak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. And he ſaid unto him, Man, who made me a Judge or a divider over you? <hi>Numb.</hi> 34.17.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It ſhews that inheritances were to be divided amongſt brethren by the law.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It was the work of the Judge to ſee it done, if complained of. That this was not at all, or not rightly (that is, juſtly) done between this man and his brother.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That there was uſually to be a divider; they were not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it themſelves by the law, that occaſions of injuſtice, and of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and diſcontent, may be removed, and occaſion of probate of wills ceaſe; only ſet a part for paying the debts, and divide the reſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It was the work of one made a Judge by the people in the way of the law, and not of others, which had not authority; which au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Chriſt aſſumed not, <hi>John</hi> 3.17. &amp; 8.15.</p>
                  <p>Ye children, judge ye if the way of the Lord be not good and ſweet, better and ſweeter then your fathers love unto you; and if he careth not more for you, then they.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute. In caſe ſome were poor, and had ſold their inheritance.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.4. There is none to redeem it beſides thee, and I am after thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Thoſe had right to redeem, came into it ſucceſſively and in order, on the refuſal thereof, <hi>Jerm.</hi> 32.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſervants.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.12. <hi>If thy brother ſerve thee ſix years, the ſeventh he ſhall go out free.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.2. <hi>If thou buy an Hebrew ſervaent, ſix yeers he ſhall ſerve: in the ſeventh he ſhall go out free for nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> If a man would buy a ſervant, he could not buy him for a longer tearm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.5. If the ſervant will not go forth free, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. he was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118573:25"/>to bring him to the judges; to ſhew, he kept him not by conſtraint, but free conſent. Note: this liberty ſervants now have, after ſeven yeers, to abide longer if they pleaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.16, 17. Shews the ground of his ſtay, that on experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had of the ſeven yeers paſt ſervice, that it was well with him, he loved him and his houſe, he might remaine.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 15.13. <hi>When thou ſendeſt him out free from thee, thou ſhalt not ſuffer him to go away empty,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt furniſh him liberally out of thy flock, out of thy flour and wine-preſs, wherewith God hath bleſſed thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe. 18. <hi>It ſhall not ſeem hard unto thee, when thou ſendeſt him away free,</hi> &amp;c. to which God promiſed a bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.26, 27. <hi>If a man ſmite out his man or maid-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants eye or tooth, they ſhall go out free therefore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 23.15. <hi>If a ſervant eſcape from his maſter, thou ſhalt not deliver him unto him: he ſhall dwell with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To explain this ſtatute, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.46. God forbids ruling with rigor, for which cauſe the ſervant ran away, and was not by the Judge to be delivered his maſter: which is illuſtrated, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.6, 8. <hi>Sarah</hi> dealing hardly with <hi>Hagar,</hi> ſhe fled from her face: and in <hi>One ſimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 24.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not oppreſs the hireling of his wages that is poor and needy, whether of thy brethren or ſtrangers; but ſhalt at his day give him his wages: nor ſhall the Sun go down on it: for he is poor, and ſets his heart upon it,</hi> Levit. 19.13.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.20. <hi>If a man ſmite his ſervant with a rod</hi> (a thing for correction, not a ſword) <hi>and he or ſhe dye under his hand, he ſhall be ſurely puniſhed.</hi> Verſ. 21. <hi>If he continue a day or two, he ſhall not be puniſhed, for he is his money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. the ſervant was to reſt and ſanctifie the Sabbath day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.32. If an Ox gore a man-ſervant or maid, the owner ſhall pay the maſter thirty ſhekels (and the Ox ſhall be ſtoned) which was one pound ſeventeen ſhillings and ſix pence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> If this were for a law, how good were it for ſervants, who now are as ſlaves for ten yeers; and at the end, their maſters, inſtead of giving ought, ſeek to ruine them? It would be good for maſters alſo; did they obey, God would bleſs them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118573:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The manner of the Jews contracts, in the buying and ſelling of their lands, is ſet down,</hi> Jer. 32.7, 8, 9, 10.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There was a right of redemption in the next of kin, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhould, if he could, buy it; if not, he muſt have the refuſe, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had, though in the priſon.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Hananeel</hi> is neceſſitated to do it, it ſeems, by crying, <hi>I pray thee buy it:</hi> and indeed, without great neceſſity, the Jews, for the evil and reproach thereof, would not do it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vid. Gen. <hi>23.</hi> Abraham <hi>purchaſing</hi> Mamre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. This was onely in free purchaſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.1. He bought the field of the owner.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He weighed the money; in which was much juſtice: there was the number, ſeventeen ſhekles; and weight alſo: and in the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, much wrong may be done in payments, though not uſed with us.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He weighed to him, the man himſelf, the money.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. Is a repetition of that in the ninth, more fully ſetting down,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That he gave <hi>Hananeel</hi> an evidence, and ſubſcribed and ſealed it, to pay for the land ſo much money; to which were wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes had ſubſcribed their names to the conditions between them; who alſo were to ſee the payment of the moneys: and this as in the 11. <hi>verſe</hi> was rolled up: none but the buyer, ſeller, and witneſſes knew.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. Is another evidence, called the evidence of the purchaſe, which was given by <hi>Hananeel;</hi> which was open.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. The evidence of the purchaſe is not kept by the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer, but by ſome officer intruſted therewith, for the publike, then called Baruch, a Scribe. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 36.26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This was done in the ſight of him that ſold it, <hi>Hananeel;</hi> which was a confirmation of the thing to the publike officer.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To this book of the purchaſe alſo there were witneſſes had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted their hands for confirmation, as the former to that writing given <hi>Hananeel</hi> for payment of the money.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Theſe witneſſes ſubſcribed the book of the purchaſe, before
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118573:26"/>many Jews, in a judicial way called to fit in the Court of the priſon.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In the preſence of theſe, it was delivered to Baruch.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. After the payment of the money that he gave <hi>Hananeel,</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him, and kept with the other of the purchaſe, for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his title: much is the conſideration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Parents, ſee, I pray, what honour God requires of your children to give you, and to obey you, and to be put to death if they do not obey you. Oh, but again diſcharge your duty, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> did, and as God commands you to do, that they may know their duty, and what in the law is commanded them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God and men in general, and you and them in eſpecial, as in <hi>Deuteronom.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10. <hi>Deuteronom.</hi> 11.19. theſe are the things you are to teach your children, ſpeaking of them when you are ſitting in the houſe, when ye walk by the way, when ye lye down and riſe up: theſe ye are to write on the door-poſts of your houſes and gates; and not ballads, and ſongs, and laſcivious pictures, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. which lead them to diſobedience againſt God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Note.</hi> It is ſaid (<hi>Deut.</hi> 21.21.) of the diſobedient child, that was a drunkard and a glutton, he ſhould be ſtoned to death; and ſo they ſhould put away evil from among them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Signifying this, that unleſs this courſe were taken with drunken diſobedient children, the evil of drunkenneſs and diſobedience to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents would not be removed out of the land. And who are there that are accuſtomed to drunkenneſs in the time of their age, that were not accuſtomed to it in youth?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For the neglect of doing juſtice in this caſe, ſee but how theſe ſins, like a leproſie or ſpreading evil, have as it were infected the poor and rich, old and young, in all parts of the Nation; and no other way but this is ever able to put away the evil thereof from amongſt us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. You muſt do ſo, that is, ſtone him to death, and not put him to death any other way; and then all the men, even his own compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, muſt help ſtone him to death, that are of the fame City: which could not but work ſtrangely on them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In Cities is uſually moſt exceſs and company-keeping.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is moſt drunkenneſs, and conſequently moſt diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for drunken children are diſobedient children.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118573:26"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Here it ſhould be done, for the greater terror to others.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Note,</hi> That the Statutes and judgements expreſſed in the word, are a rule for every Judge in each City to put in execution.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But if caſes fall out not clearly expreſſed or ſet down, called diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult caſes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe caſes are to be referred to the chief judicatory provided in that behalf, called the ſeventy or Synedry. So that here is no ſtraitedneſs for rule in the way of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They are not left to do what they will, for it muſt be the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.11.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. They are to teach, to ſhew, to tell the ſentence, out of, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law, as appears by comparing <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. with <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12. hence called Councellors, not Judges.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This was to be done by the Judge before whom it was firſt brought; he was to ſeek the reſolution thereof at the ſupreme judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory or councel.</p>
                  <p>That of <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. rulers of tens to judge, was only proper to that time, before they came into Canaan; untill when, the rule was not ſetled.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Sixth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not kill.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Statute.</hi> Gen. 9.6.</head>
                  <p>LEvit. 24.17. <hi>He that killeth a man ſhall ſurely be put to death,</hi> Numb. 35.16. <hi>If any ſmite his neighbour with an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of iron that he dye, he is a murtherer: he ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If he ſmite him with throwing of a ſtone,</hi> That he dye, he is a murtherer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If he ſmite him with a hand-weapon of wood,</hi> That he dye, he is a murtherer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If he thruſt him of hate,</hi> That he dye, he is a murtherer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Or hurle at him by lying in waite,</hi> That he dye, he is a murtherer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Or in enmity ſmite him with his hand,</hi> That he dye, he is a murtherer.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118573:27"/>
                  <p>Exod. 21.12. <hi>He that ſmiteth a man that he dye,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 14. <hi>If any come preſumptuouſly on his neighbour, and ſtay him with guile, then thou ſhalt take him from mine altar,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Kings 2.5 29, 30.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 22. <hi>If men ſtrive and hurt a woman with child and hurt felloweth</hi> (that is, afterward ſhe loſeth her life.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Gal. 5.21. <hi>Shall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſhall ſurely dye,</hi> 2 Sam. 1. from verſe 6. to the 16.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.14. <hi>Take him from the altar and put him to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Note.</hi> The executioner is to be the avenger of bloods; who was to do it when he met with him, being his near kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The avenger of blood purſued him, and ſlew him where he met with him. This would not be ſo convenient, families being diſperſt in another nature among us then them.</p>
                  <p>Queſtion is, If any other might be an executioner in this caſe, and whether the revenge of blood be to be delayed at all.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.24 27. If a man were ſlain by one not his enemy, nor ſought his hurt, the Congregation were to judge between the ſlayer and revenger, and deliver the ſlayer out of the hand of the revenger: yet if the ſlayer come out of the borders of the City, and the avenger meet with him, and ſlay him, he ſhall not be guilty of blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> This anſwered to our Jury; and in no caſe was the Jury made uſe of, but this, as I know of; which was the whole congregation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Here was matter of life and death.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The law was diverſe in this caſe, according as it did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, whether the murder were wilful or not: they were to judge with the Judge; and the congregation, not the Judge, deliver him, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.25.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What warrant this is to their proceedings in other caſes, I know not, from the law of God: for the law of God having expreſly ſet down in it the judgement of God, there needs no Jury, the fact being proved by the witneſſes that they might judge, or elſe not, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1, 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118573:27"/>
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Numb. 35.22, 23. <hi>If he thruſt ſuddenly without enmity or eaſt any thing on him without lying in wait, or with any ſtone wherewith a man may dye, ſeeing him not, and was not his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my nor ſought his harme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 4.24. <hi>If he kill his neighbour unawares and hated him not in time paſt</hi>—</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.5. An inſtance is ſet down of a man killed by the head of an Ax falling ignorantly from the helve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He ſhall flye to the City of refuge, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 20.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhall ſtay to the death of the high-Prieſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Congregation ſhall judge between the avenger and the ſlayer, when the caſe is not clear whether he ſlew the man in malice or not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.11, 12. If he ſlew him in malice, he was to be brought from the City of refuge, and delivered to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he did not, he was to abide in the City.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 21.13. <hi>If a man lye not in waite for his neighbor but God deliver him into his hand, I will appoint a place where he ſhall flee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſtion is, whether ſuch Cities, ſeeing ſuch caſes are daily among us, are not to be ſet up, to prevent ſhedding of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether that Ceremony of ſtaying in the City untill the death of the high-prieſt, do deſtroy all morality in the reſt; or rather, that now Chriſt is dead, the congregation having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted the man ſlew his brother unawares, he ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately free, by the blood and death of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.28. <hi>If an ox were wont to puſh in time paſt, and it hath been teſtified to his owner in time paſt, and he hath not kept him, but he hath killed man or woman</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118573:28"/>
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Ox ſhall be ſtoned.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His ſleſh ſhall not be eaten.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. His owner ſhall be put to death.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This ſentence by a mulct was only in this caſe to be taken off from the man: <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. <hi>If there be laid a ſum of money on him, then he ſhall give for the ranſom of his life whatſoever is laid on him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Here is no benefit of Clergy granted, nor in no caſe elſe is there any like thereunto inſtituted of God to be uſed in judgement.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The laying on him a ſum was Arbitrary.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The quantity of money was Arbitrary; he muſt pay whatever it was, or dye. <hi>Job</hi> 2.4. <hi>All a man hath will he give for his life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. What is ſaid of an Ox, may be ſaid and done of like hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful beaſts.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Why the Ox is to be killed, I think is, becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>He that ſheddeth</hi> (as well beaſt as man) <hi>mans blond, his blood ſhall be ſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.28. <hi>If an Ox gore a man or woman that they dye</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Oxe ſhall be ſurely ſtoned.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His fleſh ſhall not be eaten.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The owner ſhall be quit.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 31. <hi>Whether he hath gored ſon or daughter, according to this judgement it ſhall be done unto him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. This is the judgement of him who before had not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed unto him that it would puſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> To Judges: Whether ye can diſpence with the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, for the Ox, in his manner of death or fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 12.8. <hi>If thou build a new houſe, thou ſhalt make bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telments
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118573:28"/>on the roof, that thou bring not blood on thy houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Queſt. 1. Whether the houſe were to be deſtroyed. 2. Or a mulct to be laid thereon for the owner to pay.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 24.16. <hi>The fathers ſhall not be put to death for the children, nor children for the fathers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 21.1. <hi>If a man be found ſlain in the land, lying in the field, and not known who ſlew him</hi>— verſ. 2. <hi>The Elders and the Judges ſhall come forth, and meaſure to the Cities that are round about him that is ſlaine: the Elders of the City that are next to him ſhall take a red heifer,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ceremony of the heifer then, is the duty of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Caſe is often, and ſhews the dwellers between Cities were judged by the next City Judges, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 18.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The duty is neceſſary, that judgement for innocent blood be not brought upon us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By this means God may be intreated to reveal the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and men ſhew their innocency and clearneſs in the thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 21.22. <hi>If a man hath committed ſin worthy of death, and he be to be put to death</hi> (which was firſt done) <hi>and thou hang him on a tree:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 23. <hi>His body ſhall not remaine all night on the tree, but thou ſhalt in any wiſe bury him that day; for he that is hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is accurſed of God: that thy land be not defiled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. 1. Whether men may condemne by the law of God a man to be hanged before dead.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether men may let a man hang one the tree all night.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether a defilement of our land be not now, as well
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118573:29"/>as heretofore the Jews land thereby; and what ceremony there could be in that.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whether the judgement be Gods a man is judged by, and not the puniſhment; we uſing not Gods, but the Roman puniſhments.</p>
                  <p>Note. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth on a tree.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, the ſentencing any to death, was not of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial law, but the moral or judicial.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The curſe of the law to thoſe under the law, is as well ſince Chriſt as before.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A Nation, as I remember, were never curſed through any ceremonies; they belonged to the ceremonial law. Now in this, not only Chriſts, but all before and ſince are under the curſe of the law judicial, in which was no ceremonies: Chriſt condemned by the law, by falſe witneſſes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The condemnation was death.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The curſe was, after death to be hanged on a tree. Now ſhall we put men under the curſe of the law, God hath not put under the curſe of the law? Is it not enough that many dye when God ſaith they ſhould not dye, as in caſe of theft; but that they ſhould be accurſed by the law alſo, after death?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 24.18. <hi>He that killeth a beaſt ſhall make it good, beaſt for beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.18. <hi>If men ſtrive together, and one ſmite another with a ſtone, or with his fiſt; and he dye not, but keepeth his bed</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Iudgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. If he riſe againe, and walk abroad upon his ſtaffe, then ſhall he that ſmote him be quit.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhall pay for the loſs of his time.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He ſhall be throughly healed.</p>
                  <p>Queſtion is, whether a man walking abroad, and after in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118573:29"/>twelve moneths and a day dying, or how long before he be quit, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no time is ſet down.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This muſt be with a ſtone or fiſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This caſe is in caſe a man dyeth not.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That he keepeth his bed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That he riſe again and recover.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.22. <hi>If men ſtrive, and hurt a woman with child' ſo that her fruit depart from her, and yet no miſchief follow</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He ſhall be ſurely puniſhed (or whipt) as the womans husband will lay on him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Judge arbitrarily may lay a pecuniary mulct on him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If miſchief follow, life ſhall be for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, burning for burning, wound for wound, and ſtripe for ſtripe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 24.19. <hi>If a man cauſe a blemiſh in his neighbour</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>As he hath done, ſhall it be done unto him, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, breach for breach, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.39, 40. do not deſtroy this judicial law, the one being given by <hi>Moſes</hi> for judgement to judge thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law by in the world; the other given by Chriſt to men in the Church to live by, who, <hi>verſ.</hi> 47, are required to do more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 25.11. <hi>When men ſtrive together, and the wife of the one draws neer to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that ſmiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the ſecrets</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt cut off her hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118573:30"/>
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 24.16. <hi>No man ſhall take the nether or the upper mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to pledge, for he taketh a mans life to pledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 10. <hi>If thou lend, thou ſhalt not go into his houſe for a pledge; thou ſhalt ſtand abroad: and he to whom thou lendeſt, ſhall bring it to thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the man be poor, thou ſhalt not ſleep with his pledge, but deliver it againe when the Sun ſets, that he may ſleep in his own raiment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 17. <hi>Shall not take the widdows raiment to pledge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.21. <hi>Thou ſhalt neither vex a ſtranger, nor oppreſs him: ye ſhall not afflict any widdow nor fatherleſs child.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not curſe the deaf, nor put a ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-block before the blind.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.17, 18, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate, but rebuke thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and not ſuffer ſin upon him, nor avenge nor bear grudge againſt him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Numb. 35.31. <hi>Ye ſhall take no ſatisfaction for the life of a murderer which is guilty of death; but he ſhall be ſurely put to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of how much evil and blood-guiltineſs is this Nation guilty of! <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. defile not therefore the land by traditions of men. How hath this law been made void in times paſſed!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> If the rule and government of God were reſtored, many occaſions of murther would be prevented, all incouragements there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto taken away, and the fear of God fall on men, to keep them from doing of it; and bloodguiltineſs from the land removed, and the cauſes of the many plagues of peſtilence which uſually came with the deaths of the former princes for defiling of the land with blood in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118573:30"/>he time of their rule, with the famines of food, and judgements of unſeaſonable weather, and blaſtings, mildews, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which the Nation lyeth dyed with; not only with unrevenged blood for blood, but with blood of men put to death, which God would not have put to death; as precious Martyrs, and poor theeves: and many God would have had put to death, as adulterers, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and many God would not have put to death, as unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed men for raviſhing maidens; all which that hath been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſince the Nation hath had the word of God among them, and eſpecially ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth's dayes, wherein hath been much more free uſe and abundant knowledge of it then before, crieth to God againſt us for our blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Here ſee the neceſſity of our making a covenant with God, of ſetting up his rule and government, if ever we hope to be free from the wrath and judgement of God in our ſelves or families.</p>
                  <p>Our land hath been greatly polluted in the way of puniſhments executed contrary to Gods laws, by impriſonments, hanging, and other tortures, for law and judgement, borrowed from the heathens: and here ſee the irregularity of mans nature, who rather would be led by the corrupt rule and practice of the heathens, and their law and judgments, then the pure, juſt, and unqueſtionable way and rule of Gods word.</p>
                  <p>If by the law there is no uſe for a Jury, but in that caſe of tryal of murther, when it was not clear whether it was ſo or man-ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and then not of any choſen men, but the Congregation were to judge; this would be a great eaſe of expence to the Commonweal, if ſervice of Juries were removed.</p>
                  <p>The Judge, the plaintiff the defendant, and witneſſes, being all to ſit publikely in the gate of the City, for all to hear,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the matter were by the witneſſes made clear, and the caſe plainly ſet down in the law, the Judgement was to be ſet forth and ſhewn out of the book of God to all, and the Judges to judge, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the witneſſes made not the charge clear, then the Judges could not judge them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If there were but one witneſs, the Judges could not judge them in any caſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If the caſe were not plainly ſet down in the law to Judge by,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118573:31"/>they were not to judge them, but to transfer it to the ſupreme Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In ſtead of the priſoners putting himſelf in his tryall on God and the country, every man by covenanting with God, if he tranſgreſs, puts himſelf on God and <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whereas Juryes are for diſpatch of the multiplicity of cauſes and tryals in the ſeveral places of judgement, and joyned with the Judges, becauſe of the long diſtance of time between Aſſize and Aſſize, and then becauſe it is held but in one place of a ſhire, whence ariſeth vaſt charge to the Nation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Judgement being adminiſtred daily, without delay.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In every corner of the County being to be had, the Judges would not be ſtraitned in time for hearing of cauſes, nor would there be any need for any Juryes to help them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In ſtead of the country, the man hath <hi>Moſes;</hi> in ſtead of mans law, he hath Gods to put himſelf on.</p>
                  <p>But that I am altogether unacquainted with what concern the law or its proceedings that is among us, I might ſet more fully the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the abrogating of the one, and the eſtabliſhing the other, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Sixth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.14.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEvit.</hi> 20.10. The man that committeth adultery with another mans wife—</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. He that committeth adultery with his neighbours wife—</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. With his fathers wife, or daughter-law—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Shall not inherit the kingdom of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>They both ſhall be put to death; they have defiled themſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118573:31"/>with each other. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.1.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.38.40. <hi>Judges</hi> 19. &amp; 23. <hi>chap. Gen.</hi> 34.2, 25, 26, 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.22. <hi>If a man be found lying with a woman maried to a husband, they ſhall both of them dye,</hi> Numb. 25.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.23. <hi>If a damoſel, a virgine that is betrothed to an husband, and a man finde her in the City, and lye with her.</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They both ſhall be ſtoned at the gate of the City, the damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, becauſe ſhe cryed not; and the man, becauſe he humbled his neighbors wife.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.25. <hi>If a man finde a betrothed damoſel in the field, and the man force her and lye with her, he ſhall dye; but to the damoſel ye ſhall do nothing: for as when a man riſeth againſt his neighbour and ſlayeth him, ſo is this matter,</hi> verſ. 27. <hi>He found her in the field; ſhe cryed, and there was none to ſave her.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.28. <hi>If a man finde a damoſel not betrothed, a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and lay hold on her and lye with her, and they be found</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He laid hold on her, and lay with her: he ſhall give her father fifty ſhekels, three pound two ſhillings and ſix pence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She ſhall be his wife; he hath humbled her.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He ſhall not put her away all his dayes.</p>
                  <p>If any man ſhould have dyed for fornication, this man ſhould; but is not to dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.16. <hi>If a man intice a maid that is not betrothed, and lye with her</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:118573:32"/>
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He ſhall ſurely indow her to be his wife.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. If her father utterly refuſe to give her to him to wife (as in this caſe he might) he ſhall pay money according to the dowry of virgins.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Note, Before, a man <hi>laid hold</hi> on a maid; he here <hi>inticeth</hi> a maid; and the maid conſenting, the fifty ſhekels are not paid her father, three pound two ſhillings ſix pence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Here note, all raviſhments do not deſerve death, as by our law: and though we ſay God would not have that ſeverity uſed under the Goſpel as under the law, we in many caſes uſe more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 20.14. <hi>If a man take a wife and her mother</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He and they ſhall be burned with fire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.6. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. are expreſſed the prohibited degrees of conſanguinity and affinity; within which men are not to marry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.21. <hi>If a man lye with his uncles or brothers wife, they ſhall be childleſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>That is, before the time of child-bearing, they both ſhould be put to death: others, only a curſe of barrenneſs, which cannot be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.18. If a man lye with a woman having her ſickneſs, and uncover her nakedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They both ſhall be cut off from among the people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> If by death, or as <hi>Miriam,</hi> ſhut out without the campe.</p>
                  <p>It is of great note, that the reaſon why the widdows portion was to be ſo ſmal of her husbands eſtate, was, becauſe her father was to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118573:32"/>provide for her; or her husbands brethren, if ſhe had no children; and her children, if ſhe had any.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.17. If a man take his ſiſter, his fathers or his mothers daughter, and ſee her nakedneſs, or ſhe ſee his —</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>It is a wicked thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall be cut off from among the people.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.29. <hi>Do not proſtitute thy daughter to cauſe her to be a whore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 18.22. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lye with man-kind as with woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 20.13. <hi>If a man lye with man-kind as with woman</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>They both have committed abomination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall ſurely be put to death, their blood ſhall be upon them.</hi> This phraſe ſhews the ground of the Jews cry, <hi>His blood be on us and our children,</hi> Mat. 27.25. when <hi>Pilate</hi> waſhed his hands as innocent of Chriſts death; which being innocent, he ſhould have juſtified.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.19. <hi>Whoſoever lyeth with a beaſt</hi>—</p>
                  <p>Levit. 18.23. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lye with any beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 20.15. <hi>If a man lye with a beaſt</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>It is a defiling of a mans ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The man ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The beaſt ſhall be ſlain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118573:33"/>
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.5. <hi>A woman ſhall not wear that appertains to a man, nor a man that appertaines to a womans garment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 18.23. <hi>A woman ſhall not ſtand before a beaſt, to lye down thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 20.16. <hi>If a woman approach to a beaſt, and lye down thereunto</hi>—</p>
                  <p>Levit. 18.26. Which the ſtranger was forbid, as well as the home-borne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is ſaid to be <hi>confuſion or mixture of contrary natures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The land and people are defiled thereby.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thou ſhalt kill the woman, and the beaſt; their blood ſhall be upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. God caſt out and the land vomited out the heathens therefore, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.24, 25. and would ſpew them out alſo, if they did the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 21.7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take a whore to wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 22.20. <hi>If a man take a wife, and ſhe be not a virgine, and he accuſe her to the elders of the City, and her parents can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhew the tokens of her virginity</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall bring her out to the door of her fathers houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>There the men of her City ſhall ſtone her with ſtones that ſhe dye, becauſe ſhe wrought folly in Iſrael, to play the whore in her fathers houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>So</hi> (and no otherwayes) <hi>ſhalt thou put away evil</hi> (that is, the Judge) <hi>from among you.</hi> Then, by doing this juſtice on her, which would be a means of preventing much evil.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Note.</hi> Elders, not Judges, had the ordinance of marriage referred to them: which were twelve. Vid. <hi>Topſel</hi> on <hi>Ruth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:118573:33"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Adultery before marriage, as well as after, diſſolves marriage, and is puniſhed with death: which would make parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren more careful of their childrens converſation and company in youth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A tradition uſed among us, hath made void this law of God; we ſaying, when a man married a woman, that he was to take her <hi>for better, for worſe;</hi> ſo as that though ſhe were a whore, ſhe was now to be his wife, and no remedy left him to deliver himſelf: which gave all manner of liberty and looſeneſs to maidens before marriage, and occaſioned looſeneſs in their converſations afterward; which is a thing expreſly againſt the law of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.13. <hi>If a man take a wife, and go in to ber, and hate her,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>and give un occaſion of ſpeech againſt her, and bring an evil name upon her, and ſay, I took this woman, and when I came to her, I found her not a maid;</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>The father and mother of the damoſel ſhall bring forth the tokens of her virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to the Elders of the City, in the City, in the gate;</hi> verſ. 17. <hi>And they ſhall ſpread the cloth before the Elders of the City,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. They ſhall <hi>chaſtiſe,</hi> that is, whip <hi>the man:</hi> now in whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the man was to have but fourty ſtripes; nor was he to ſtand, but lye down.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall amerce him a hundred ſhekels of ſilver, and give them the father of the damoſel;</hi> which is ſix pound five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>She ſhall be his wife; he may not put her away all his dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. A bill of divorce might be given others, but not this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe that by the report ſhe was defamed, another would not take her.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Without this law, he would not keep her a day; he hated her before, but worſe now.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>This caſe is illuſtrateed in ſome kind, by</hi> Joſeph <hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>Math.</hi> 1.18.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He eſpouſed <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118573:34"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Before they come together, ſhe is found with child.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He being a juſt man, was not willing to make her a publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (that is, to have her ſtoned) <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He was minded to put her away (not to marry her) privately, to leave her and forſake her.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20. The Angel ſaid, <hi>Fear not to take to thee</hi> Mary <hi>thy wife.</hi> Here by fear is ſignified <hi>Joſephs</hi> fearing to marry her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods command, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.17. he not knowing that what was conceived in her was of the Holy Spirit, untill revealed to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Here it is not amiſs to ſpeak of marriage, the means or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God to prevent adultery.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. This ordinance was not pertaining to the Prieſts, for it was belonging to <hi>Moſes</hi> and was before the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron;</hi> and is lawful among heathens, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor to the Judges.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It belonged to the Elders in the City. Now there were to be Judges and Elders in the Commonwealth-government: hence mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters pertaining to man and wife are uſually referred to the Elders, that concern marriage, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.7, 8, 9, &amp; 22.15, 17, 18. and not to the Judges.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.2. <hi>Boaz</hi> took ten men of the Elders of the City, for number.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They ſate down in the gate of the City, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. for the place where civil affairs were diſcuſs'd of.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. He calls Elders and people to witneſs, he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed <hi>Ruth</hi> to wife: the dowry of a widdow was twenty five, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but half of a maids, which was fifty ſhekels.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. The people and Elders ſay, <hi>We are witneſſes;</hi> and bleſs them both. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. Theſe are not to be Elders of the Church, <hi>James</hi> 5.14. but of the Commonweal only.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. He took <hi>Ruth,</hi> and ſhe was his wife; and he went in unto her, and ſhe conceived and bare a ſon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Concluſion. If the ordinance belong to <hi>Moſes,</hi> then for any other, under what pretence ſoever, to do it, it is high preſumption.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are married by them, are not joyned in the way of the Lord, nor by that authority God ordained among thoſe that have his law.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118573:34"/>
                  <p n="3">3. I ſay of this, as of acts done by Heathens, without law, that <hi>they are a law to themſelves:</hi> ſo are our doings in this matter this day: It were good it were amended. Never did Prieſt, Levite, Chriſt, or Apoſtle, do it for any; and then by what authority do the miniſtry now do it?</p>
                  <p>Here I deſire leave to commend to your conſideration that one branch in the Act made for adultery, <hi>May</hi> 10. 1650.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If any man ſhall have the carnal knowledge of the body of any virgine, unmarryed woman, or widdow, every ſuch man and woman convict of ſuch offence,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Shall be committed to common goale three moneths.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Shall give ſecurity to be of the good bahaviour for one whole yeer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> 1. If the man be a young man or widdower, then he was to marry the maid, or unmarryed woman, or widdow, by the law of God, and not to be priſoned, bound, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he be a marryed man, then the caſe is adultery, as in the womans before that was marryed to another man; and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment death.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If you had put them to death by Gods law, ye would not have ſaid it ſhould be death after ſuch a day; Gods law not taking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning then, nor eſtabliſhment from us; or at leaſt until then, we were not under Gods law, nor was it declared to the nation in the name of Gods law, but mans, as an Act of Parliament onely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.20. <hi>Whoever lyeth carnally with a woman that is a bondmaid</hi> (or apprentice) <hi>betrothed to an husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>She ſhall be ſcourged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall not be put to death, becauſe ſhe was not free.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This, nor many other caſes, are not excepted in the late Act.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 20.11, 12. <hi>The man that lieth with his fathers wife or daughter-law</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:118573:35"/>
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are to be put to death; their blood ſhall be upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this law only adulterers dye: the man, becauſe he humbled his neighbours wife, whether betrothed onely or marryed: the woman, becauſe ſhe broke the covenant of her God. In which is much juſtice.</p>
                  <p>In this law, raviſhments of ſuch as are unmarryed, and neither of them betrothed, are freed from death, either by marriage, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or penal puniſhments: which is of exceeding mercy.</p>
                  <p>Who ſhall do more in one, or leſs in the other, and be innocent before God? O where is law, or juſtice, or mercy, or righteouſneſs, but in this law of the Lord! how then ſhall we yet juſtifie and ſet up our own, and condemne and ſuppreſs the law of the Lord!</p>
                  <p>This command is broken by intemperance, or inſobriety, in meat, drink, and apparel; the evil whereof, eſpecially that of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, abounds in this Nation, and is very great before the Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Command.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wo to him that giveth his neighbour drink, that putteſt thy bottle to him, and makeſt him drunken, that thou mayeſt look on their nakedneſs,</hi> Habac. 2.15, 16. deprived of his place in Church and world, as a maſter, an owner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.8. In <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> great feaſt, the drinking was <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the law; none did compel,</hi> for <hi>the king had appointed to all the officers of his houſe, that they ſhould do according to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans pleaſure.</hi> It is emphatical: God diſtinguiſheth his law from the ſtatutes of Kings: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.36. Yet this is to be obſerved, though it ſerves for a law with us, being ſanctified, and become part of the word of God; in which it excells other kings laws, though it come ſhort of Gods. By this word, the other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the King are ſet forth.</p>
                  <p>Iſa. 5.11. <hi>Wo to them riſe up early in the morning that they may follow ſtrong drink, that continue until night that wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame them; and the harp and pipe, and viol are in their feaſts,</hi> &amp;c. Verſ. 22. <hi>Wo to them are mighty to drink wine, and men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drink.</hi> Iſa. 56.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come ye, ſay they, we will fetch wine, and will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:118573:35"/>
                  <p>Mat. 24.49. <hi>He was the evil ſervant eat and drank with the drunken.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quer.</hi> Whether <hi>the violence of Lebanon,</hi> a holy violence, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.17. be not of <hi>Habakkuks</hi> drunkenneſs, that his eſtate be taken from him, and beſtowed on thoſe are to inherit, to preven the evil on his family, the land, and City. Thus in <hi>Abigail,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2 5.18.19.</p>
                  <p>Gal. 5. — Shall not inherit the kingdome of God. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. the Church-drunkards had the plague among them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11. Wine and drunkenneſs take away the heart, <hi>Deut,</hi> 29.19 20.</p>
                  <p>Iſa. 28.3. <hi>The crown of pride, the drunkards of Ephraim ſhall be troden under foot;</hi> have no imployment nor honor among men, but be as that veſſel in whom is no delight.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 4. <hi>Their beauty and glory</hi> (which conſiſts in riches and greatneſs) <hi>ſhall be as a fading flower, and haſty fruit, before ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> Joel 1.5. God would have one generation tell another, that the plagues of palmer, canker, locuſt, were for drunkenneſs.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 7. <hi>The prieſt and prophet err through wine and ſtrong drink, they err in viſion; and ſtumble in judgement, and are out of the way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 8. <hi>All tables are full of vomit and filthineſs, ſo that there is no place clean.</hi> 1 Sam. 25.36.37. Prov. 23.20, 21, 29, 30.</p>
                  <p>Hab. 2.16. <hi>Thou art filled with ſhame for glory: drink thou alſo, and let thy foreskin be uncovered.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The word in the original ſignifieth the taking away of one out of his place.</note> 
                     <hi>The cup of the Lords right hand ſhall be turned to thee, and ſhameful ſpewing ſhall be one thy glory.</hi> Verſ. 17. <hi>The violence of Lebanon ſhall cover thee, and the ſpoile of heaſts which made them afraid, becauſe of mens blood, and for the violence of the land, and the City, and all that dwell therein,</hi> Gen. 9.23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.13. This drunkenneſs brought forth, that in which King, Prieſts, Prophets, inhabitants, fathers, and ſons, became drunk ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually; and daſh one againſt another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18. The ſon on his fathers exhortation would not leave his drunkenneſs, was ſtoned, as in <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. by all the men of his City.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="commandment">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118573:36"/>
               <head>Command the Eighth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Statute.</hi> Levit. 27.28, 29.</head>
                  <p>PSalm 76.12. <hi>Vow, and pay to the Lord, all ye that are round about him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat thy vows thou voweſt to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. The caſe of vows is handled, when lawful, when not, in a man, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. a maid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. &amp; 5. a wife, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8. a widdow, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. to the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Jephthah, <hi>Judges</hi> 11.31, 36, 39.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not to pay, is ſacriledge or theft from God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The puniſhment exemplary in <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> Acts 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to the 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> To Parliament, people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to remember the vows of God on your ſouls: they are not paid; God requires them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.16. <hi>He that ſtealeth a man, and ſelleth him, or if he be found in his hand,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 24.7. <hi>If he be found making merchandiſe of an Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elite, or ſtealing of him, or ſelling of him</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prov. 28.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Levit. 19.11. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſteal nor deal falſly one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:118573:36"/>
                  <p>Exod. 22.1. <hi>If he ſteal an oxe, and kill or ſell it,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall reſtore five oxen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If he ſteal a ſheep, and kill or ſell it;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall reſtore four ſheep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 4. <hi>If the theef be found in his hand certainly and alive, whether it be oxe, aſs, or ſheep</hi>—</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall reſtore double.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Verſ. 7. <hi>If a man ſhall deliver money or ſcuff to keep, and it be ſtollen out of the mans houſe, and the theef be found,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let him pay double.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 8. <hi>If the theef be not found, then the maſter of the houſe ſhall be brought to the Judges, to ſee whether he have put his hands to his neighbours goods.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.9. <hi>For all manner of treſpaſs, whether it be for ox, for aſs, for ſheep, for raiment, or for any manner of loſt thing which another challengeth to be his, the cauſe of both parties ſhall come before the Judges; and whom the Judges ſhall cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall pay double to his neighbour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.10. <hi>If a man deliver to his neighbour an aſs, an ox, or a ſheep, or any beaſt to keep,</hi> and <hi>it dye, or be hurt, or driven away, no man ſeeing it</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. An oath of the Lord ſhall be between them both, that he hath not put his hand to his neighbours goods.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The owner ſhall accept thereof.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He ſhall not make it good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. If it be ſtollen from him, he ſhall make reſtitution to the owner thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13 If it be torn in peeces,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let him bring it for witneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:118573:37"/>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhall not make good what was torn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.2. <hi>If a theef be found breaking up, and he be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that he dye</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There ſhall no blood be ſhed for him</hi> (no, not in the member he was wounded)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.3. <hi>But if the Sun be riſen on him</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Blood ſhall be ſhed for him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhould have made ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If he have nothing, he ſhall be ſold for his theft.</p>
                  <p>The Statutes Judicial, as from their <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> were dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the ten commandments only; to which thoſe of tythes were not referred but depended on the prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and law an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. See, here is no hanging, burning, no nor whipping ſet down by God, nor Clergy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Gods aime is ſatisfaction of the loſer, and not the loſs of the goods of the honeſt man, nor life of the theef.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The theef, if he have not to pay, his body will yeeld more to ſell beyond the ſeas, then his death will do any man good: that yeelds nothing but trouble of minde.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God would not value any mans life at the rate of any goods; and he is the Lord thereof, and not man: and how ſhall we then dare do it?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Note, The man that proſecutes, the Jury, the Judge, they have all cauſe to call on the Parliament for the ſetting up of Gods law: for how ſhall they anſwer when God ſhall Judge?</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>Men condemned for ſtealing and releaſed, after come to kill a man: who is guilty of that blood?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> To take away a mans life for ſtealing goods, is to be guilty of his blood, becauſe God, the onely Judge, ſaith he ſhall not dye.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:118573:37"/>
                  <p n="2">2. When the man ſlew a man, his blood was on his own head: before he was not, now he was appointed to dye.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As Chriſt to the man, ſo may ye ſay to ſuch, <hi>Go thy way, ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing happen unto thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O let us remember we are men, and under a judgement: how ſhall we do, if God meaſure to us as we meaſure to others? the meaſure of the mans ſin that ſtole was not full, untill he had killed. Now God ſaith to the man he will deſtroy. <hi>Fill up the meaſure of thy ſin:</hi> and how ſhall he do it, if we take him away before? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.5. <hi>If a man ſhall cauſe a field or vineyard to be eaten, and ſhall put in his beaſt, and ſhall feed in another mans field</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the beſt of his own field, and the beſt of his own vinyard, ſhall he make ſatisfaction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 22.6. <hi>If fire break forth, and eatch in thornes, that the ſtacks of corne or ſtanding corne, or the field be conſumed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that kindled the fire ſhall ſurely make ſat is faction:</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 19.11. <hi>You ſhall not ſteal, nor deal falſty one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt not defraud thy neighbour, nor rob him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 35. <hi>Ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſs in met-yard, in weight, or meaſure: but a juſt balance, weight, epha, hin, ſhall ye have.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 25.13. <hi>Thon ſhalt not have in thy houſe divers meaſures, a great and a ſmal; nor in thy bag divers weights, a great and a ſmall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 15. <hi>But a perfect and juſt meaſure ſhalt thou have.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:118573:38"/>
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That thou mayeſt live long in the land:</hi> God otherwayes will cut thee off.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe that do ſuch things, and do unrighteouſly, are an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination before the Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.14. <hi>If a man borrow ought of his neighbour and it be hurt or dye, and the owner not with it</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>He ſhall ſurely make it good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>But if the owner be preſent, he ſhall not make it good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>If it be a hired thing, it came for his hire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.33. <hi>If a man open a pit, or dig a pit, and not cover it, and an ox or an aſs fall therein</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The owner of the pit ſhall make it good.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He ſhall give him money for it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He ſhall have the dead beaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.35. <hi>If one mans ox hurt another that he dye</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>They ſhall ſell the dead ox, and divide the money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſell the live ox, and divide the money.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Exod. 21.36. <hi>If it be known the ox hath uſed to puſh in time paſt, and the owner hath not kept him in</hi>—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>He ſhall ſurely pay ox for ox.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:118573:38"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The dead one ſhall be his own.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Though the difference in goodneſs may be great between them, yet the penalty juſtly falls on the maſter of the killing oxe, and the judgement not to be queſtioned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.28. &amp; 23.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 19.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not remove thy neighbours landmark, which they of old time have ſet in thine inheritance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 23.24. <hi>When thou comeſt into thy neighbours vineyard, thou mayeſt eat grapes thy fill at thine own pleaſure: when thou comeſt into the ſtanding corne of thy neighbours, thou mayeſt pluck the ears with thy hand,</hi> jus charitatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not put any into thy veſſel.</hi> This, jus proprietatis.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Nor move thy ſickle to thy neigbours ſtanding corne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 22.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee thy brothers ox or ſheep go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, and hide thy ſelf from them: thou ſhalt in any caſe bring them to thy brother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 2. <hi>If thy brother be not near, and thou know him not, it ſhall be with thee until thy brother ſeek after it; and then thou ſhalt reſtore it him again.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 3. <hi>In like manner ſhalt thou do with his Aſs and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all loſt things of thy brothers,</hi> that thou haſt found, <hi>Thou mayeſt not hide thy ſelf,</hi> Verſ. 4.</p>
                  <p>Exod. 23.4. <hi>If thou ſee thy enemies Ox or Aſs going aſtray, thou ſhalt ſurely bring it back to him again.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 5. <hi>If thou ſee the Aſs of him that hateth thee lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his burden, and wouldſt for bear to help him, thou ſhalt ſurely help with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> In the laws of God is not holineſs and juſtice onely, but goodneſs. To whom will a man obey, if not God? and whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands will he do, if not his? to which is promiſed <hi>great reward</hi> to thoſe that keep them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:118573:39"/>
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend thy brother upon uſury of money or victuals, or any thing is lent on uſury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 20. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a ſtranger thou mayeſt lend on uſury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 22.25. <hi>If thou lend money to any of my people that is poor, by thee, thou ſhalt not be to them as an uſurer, nor ſhalt thou lay on him uſury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 25.35. <hi>If thy brother be waxen poor, and faln into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay with thee, then thou ſhalt relieve him, though he be a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or ſojourner with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 36. <hi>Take no uſury or increaſe of him. Thou ſhalt not give him thy money or lend him thy victual for increaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. and <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36. oppoſe one another ſeemingly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſtranger in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> is no proſelyte, and not added to the Lords people: God permitted it there, as it were, as <hi>Moſes</hi> for the hardneſs of heart gave a bill of divorce.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſtranger in <hi>Leviticus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. He is a brother, being in covenant with God, equally with him in the judicial, though not in the priviledges of the ceremonial law and worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is on a ſpecial caſe of mercy; he is faln into decay, and waxen poor: to take uſe of ſuch a one for money or victual, were biting indeed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If uſury under the legal covenant were bad, and forbid, it is worſe under grace.</p>
                  <p>It may be ſaid, <hi>The Goſpel forbids it not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Chriſts members need no ſuch prohibition, if they were true members: they <hi>have not ſo learned Chriſt,</hi> Acts 4.34. Mat. 5.42. Rom. 12.20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God under the law in the ſtate of the world, is expreſly againſt uſury, and tolerates it not by his law.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Queſtion is, Whether by toleration of uſury, we make not that law of God voide by our traditions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where is no penalty expreſſed, nor courſe ſet down, whether we are not to leave men to God and his law.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If men lend money on uſury, and the borrower refuſe to pay,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:118573:39"/>and tendering the principal, eſpecially in the caſe of a poor man, whether a Judge may force that man to pay intereſt: though it is true, by Gods law, a man is to keep his promiſe, though he loſe thereby, but then it muſt be in all juſt things.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whether contracts made to colour Uſury, are not to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as theft, deceit, cozenage, fraud, by which they go beyond their brethren, and rob them oppreſs them, and devour them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 19,8 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>I will reſtore four-fold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They gave and took ſuretiſhip for debts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.18. ſhews manner, and 20.16. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 22.26, 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 15.2. <hi>Every creditor that lendeth ought to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, at ſeven yeers ſhall releaſe it, and not exact it of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or brother: it is the Lords releaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 3. <hi>Of a foraigner thou mayeſt exact it againe; but that which is thine with thy brother, thy hand ſhall releaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> Save when there ſhall be no poor amongſt you.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 15.7. <hi>If there be a poor man amongſt you, one of thy brethren, thou ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor ſhut thy hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>but ſhalt open it wide, and lend him ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for his need.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 9. <hi>Take heed of the wicked thought in thy heart, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The ſeventh yeer of releaſe is at hand, and thine eye be evil, and thou geveſt thy brother nothing, and he cry to God againſt thee, and it be ſin unto thee.</hi> Verſ. 10. <hi>For theſe things the Lord thy God will bleſs thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> The word <hi>brother</hi> in the law ſhuts and opens many caſes; which was then applyed to men joyned in the band of the legal co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to God and one another, as in the Goſpel it ſignifies thoſe are united by baptiſme and faith to Chriſt and one another, in fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and houſe of God.</p>
                  <p>Now all thoſe that were not under the legal covenant with the Jews, were called <hi>ſtrangers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. If men will acknowledge any law, it is Gods, becauſe of his authority and power of the ſoul, as well as body.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. None ever ſtudyed the good and profit of a people as God, who is ſaid to rule over us as a father over his children, and not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:118573:40"/>as a Tyrant over ſlaves, or maſter over ſervants.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Hence, O ye princes of the people, for your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, the peoples good, and Gods glory, and the bleſſing of the earth, and men in their callings, ſet up Gods law, and the nations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe will be great that will follow, if you will believe and obey: and the good ye ſhall do in your generation for the Nation, will be ſuch, as was never done for it by any or all your predeceſſors; in which onely the people will become a free people, and no other lords beſides God rule over them.</p>
                  <p>Eraſm. <hi>Nune adulterium luſus magnatum eſt, paſſim ſaevitur in miſeros fures, cum nec draconis leges, nec Romanae, nec ullae Gentilium ſimplex furtum ſupplicio capitis vindicaverint, ſed avaritia noſtra facit ut ideo magnum malum exiſtimemus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quia pecuniam ſummus boni loco ducimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider that of <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.24. and judge if a neighbour, not with any purpoſe to wrong his neighbour, or to make a cuſtome of it, but on ſome accidental occaſion, go over his neighbours land, whether by the law of God one man in ſuch a caſe may arreſt, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſue at law, or damnifie in any caſe his neighbour.</p>
                  <p>Numb. 5.6, 7. <hi>When a man or woman commit ſin, and the perſon be found guilty, they ſhall confeſs their ſin they have done: he ſhall recompence his treſpaſs with the principal thereof, and add unto it the fifth part thereof, and give it to him againſt whom they have treſpaſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 8. <hi>But if the man have no kinſman to recompence the treſpaſs to, let the treſpaſs be recompenced unto the Lord, even to the Prieſt.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The variety of differences of the ſame meaſure, <hi>viz.</hi> the buſhel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> give occaſion to alter ours into the meaſure of the Jews Ephah, that the meaſure may be one in the whole nation, as theirs was; and ſo that occaſion of buying by one in one place, and ſelling by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in another place, may be taken away: and ſo for weights and meaſures.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>The Jews had difference among themſelves in theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> That difference was ceremonial only, as in the ſhekel of the Sanctuary, and of the Commonweal: but that cauſe is now taken away; and was inſtituted of God whiles that the temple
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:118573:40"/>did remaine to continue onely, and then to ceaſe with other cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.19. And in many other places, courſe was taken that ſomething in the harveſt ſhould be left for the poor in the field, the vineyard, the oliveyard, for the poor, the ſtranger, the fatherleſs, the widdow. <hi>Exod.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Note. Were this rule eſtabliſhed among men, the cauſe of much theft would be taken away from among men, which mens hard heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs occaſions; and after with as much ſeverity put them to death oft-times for a ſmal matter, as though God were not able to reſtore our loſs, or we could not be without it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Many late and unuſual offences as clipping and coyning of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and embaſing of it, which is made treaſon by our law, would not be ſo rife among us; the occaſion thereof being removed from men in great part.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Burning of houſes, and ſuch like effects of unnatural envy, would be removed, when oppreſſion and ignorance of the law of God were removed from the ſhoulders of the poor.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God would reſtraine men, as now he doth of much evil, to admiration, that <hi>home non ſit housini lup us;</hi> ſo then he would do much more: the fear of God, though his law, and the juſtice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be not ſo extreme as mans in this caſe, yet the after-judgement on the ſoul, and curſe of them and their families, falls far greater on men then theirs can do.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Ninth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THis negative bindes in the affirmative, <hi>Thou ſhalt bear witneſs to the truth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Statute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.6. The Idolater was not to dye at the teſtimony of one, but of two or three witneſſes.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:118573:41"/>
                  <p>Deut. 19.15. <hi>One witneſs ſhall not riſe againſt a man for any iniquity or ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 19.11. <hi>Ye ſhall not lye one unto another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 19.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not go up and down as a tale-bearer among thy people, nor ſhalt thou ſtand againſt the blood of thy neighbour,</hi> Ezek. 22.9. Prov. 21.18. <hi>He that heareth, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth conſtantly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Exod. 23.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not raiſe a falſe report: put not thy hand with the wicked, to be an unrighteous witneſs;</hi> as thoſe witneſſed againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 Kings.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil, nor ſhalt thou ſpeak in a cauſe to decline after many to wreſt judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 3. <hi>Nor ſhalt thou countenance a poor man in his cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The witneſſes at the time of execution were to ſtand at the right hand of him that was condemned, and to lay their hands on his head, and caſt the firſt ſtone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.30. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.28.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Judgement.</head>
                  <p>Deut. 27.24. <hi>Curſed be he that ſmiteth his neighbour ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deut. 19.16. <hi>If a falſe witneſs riſe up againſt any man to teſtifie againſt him, that that is wrong;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 17. <hi>Then both the men between whom the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is, ſhall ſtand before the Lord</hi> (as a ſpecial caſe referred to the chief Judges) <hi>the Prieſts and Judges that ſhall be in thoſe dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 18. <hi>The Judges ſhall make diligent inquiry, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, if the witneſs be a falſe witneſs, and hath teſtifyed falſly againſt his brother;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſ. 19. <hi>Then ſhall ye do to him as he had thought to have done unto his brother: So</hi> (and no way elſe) <hi>ſhalt thou put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way evil from among you: life for life, eye, tooth, ſtripe for ſtripe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> If Judges and Juſtices were as (they ought) at all times ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in all the chief places of the Nation,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Witneſſes would not be ſo chargeable for their journey and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to men as now they are.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:118573:41"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Men might diſcharge their conſciences, who by the law-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant were bound to witneſs freely one for other, as oft as occaſion ſerved.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Subpaena's</hi> were utterly out of uſe, and the charge thereof taken away from men.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If according to the law of God, that were exactly done on the falſe witneſs, which was intended againſt the party that was proſecuted, men in the Nation would <hi>hear indeed, and fear to do any ſuch wickedneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If evil be ſo to be put away, then by not doing ſo, though to man it ſeems to be a matter of never ſo much ſeverity, the evil there-remaines in the land ſtill.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In what was done or intended to be done by them paſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The evil practice thereof will never be done away by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means from among us, but by this.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.24. The curſe denounced againſt the falſe, and ſo the curſes added to the breach of every command, note the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Gods law and mans.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Mans law onely extended to puniſh ſin when proved by wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, againſt a man; by which men (as in caſe of adultery) fear to commit it publikely, but will do it privately; and man he thinks cannot not curſe him for it; or if he do, he cares not.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Now God curſeth ſuch by his law: ſo that though they may eſcape the publike puniſhment, they cannot the ſecret judgement or curſe for it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. So that this now will prevaile with men, when the other will not: in which the law of God doth far excell the moſt juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ordinances of man.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Theſe curſes are added to Gods laws, not mens, for fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and a puniſhment after his laws are broken, and not mens; ſo that the hand of God in the revealing and cutting off, and curſing of evil doers, will appear under his rule far otherwayes then under mens.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Effect whereof is excellently ſet down, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.18. God ſpeaks of one not regarding the curſe, and calls him <hi>the root of bitterneſs</hi> that bears gall and wormwood, who <hi>when he hears the words of this curſe, he bleſs himſelf in his heart, ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:118573:42"/>my heart to add drunkenneſs to thirſt,</hi> Verſ. 20. <hi>The Lord will not ſpare him; the anger of the Lord, and his jealouſie ſhall ſmoak againſt him; and all the curſes in this book ſhall lye upon him: and the Lord will blot out his name from under heaven,</hi> verſ. 21. <hi>and the Lord will ſeparate him unto evil out of all the tribes of Iſrael, according to all the curſes of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that are writen in this book of the law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="commandment">
               <head>Command the Tenth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not covet.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p n="1">1. S Search all the Statute-books of all the Nations in the world, they have no ſuch law in them; nor take no notice of any ſuch ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor have they any puniſhment for it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Under this law it is condemned as well as any. Hence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>The law is ſpiritual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> O ye princes, ſee here, are not Gods laws more perfect then yours? you have no ſuch law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is not your law the work of the law of God in your hearts onely? would there ever have been a law of yours, had not God given a work of his in you?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence ſee a neceſſity of taking his, and leaving yours.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Do not ſay the law is not ſufficient to judge by.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Were not the Jews as great as we? and they had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They fell into as many varieties of evil and ſin as any.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>If thou ſayeſt. No, we fall into more;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The reaſon of that is, we have not the law of God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it ſet up among us, as they had: the law of man can never have that place among a people, as the law of God hath.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not the leaſt evil againſt God, to ſay of the law, It is not ſufficient of it ſelf to judge us by.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:118573:42"/>
               <p n="1">1. If the law is not perfect, God would not have ſaid, <hi>Add not to, nor diminiſh a word from it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This is indeed to <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the law, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. which was <hi>death without mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The law was the moral law, a law for all Nations that would be Gods people, as well as Jews, to be governed by.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thy law is exceeding broad and large:</hi> but thou that knoweſt not the law, and art rude and ignorant of Gods wiſdome therein, which is a great deep, diſhonoureſt God, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it is onely for a foundation of a law, but it will not ſerve for a law. At the laſt day it ſhall judge thee and all elſe, for all their acts, words, and thoughts againſt God: and yet is it a narrow law?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Say what you can, a Nation, untill it hath covenanted with God in this law, they are not the people of God nor is God the God of that nation, more then other heathens; whatever he may be by faith to them that believe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This would be a means to call in the Jews to acknowledge Chriſt in the Goſpel with believers, when they ſee we acknowledge God in the law with them.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Theſe are but few caſes in compare of the Statute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book, that is more full, and large, and plaine: this is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. I have deduced but part of what is in the law, I having not ſpent a weeks time in meditation thereon to this end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This hath more in one line, then the wit of men laid down for law in an hundred.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they have more then is in the law of God, muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and not acknowledged law, but traditions only.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Much lyeth hid thereof to us, as yet being not ſearched out.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Judges in ſpecial were ordained to judge the difficult cauſes, and that by the word alſo, which appeared not to the common judges to be in the word clearly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The laws being reduced to the command, we are to judge of caſes according to the nature of the fact, and the command againſt which the ſin is committed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The law is clear plaine, and full of light and clearneſs; and ſo better then our corrupted, intricate, unknown law, which the Judges of the land know not themſelves. This needs no counſel.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:118573:43"/>
               <p n="2">2. It is brief, and needs not ſeven yeers ſtudy, to come to be able to ſpeak law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is ſo eaſie, a man needs no ſollicitors: it ſhews plainly what every man is to do or ſuffer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It cannot be corrupted by demurs, nor delayed in proceedings.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is ſo juſt, no man ſhall have wrong that is innocent, nor no man ſhall eſcape that is guilty; <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19, 20.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It is ſo free, it puts no man to a peny coſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is ſo holy, it condems all evil in every man alike.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is ſo good, that he is accurſed that obeys it not, and he is bleſſed that obſerves it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. It is free from oppreſſion; it impriſons none.</p>
               <p>O ye men and lawyers of the world, bring forth that law that is like this law of the Lord: as <hi>Moſes</hi> rod eat up the ſorcerers: ſo ſhall this devour yours. Your law is as darkneſs, this as light; it will make it vaniſh. In a word, all Rule and Government compared to Gods in the law, for a Nation, is but bramble-rule, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.14. and who would call for that rule?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>PSalm 144.15. <hi>Happy is the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> that is, that people onely who are in covenant with, and under the government of the Lord and his law: and thus with <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Behold, I have taught you ſtatutes and judgements, even as the Lord my God commanded me.</hi> Verſ. 6. <hi>Keep therefore and do them: for this is your wiſdome and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſight of the Nations, which ſhall hear all theſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and ſay, Surely this great nation is a wiſe and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding people.</hi> Verſ. 7. <hi>for what nation is there ſo great, that hath God ſo neer unto them as the Lord our God is in all things we call upon him for?</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>and what nation is there ſo great, that? hath ſtatutes and judgements ſo righteous as all this law which I ſet before you this day?</hi> Who can ſpeak evil of that I have here written, and not ſpeak evil of the law? who can deſpiſe it, and not deſpiſe that law ſhall judge him at the laſt day? God judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by it, let therefore the Gods judge by it. In a word, who
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:118573:43"/>are they, if any, that ſhall condemne me for what I have written? God is he that will juſtifie me, when he ſhall ariſe and plead my cauſe with them. In a word, if I have erred, the law erreth not: let me be judged by that; to that I plead, and make my appeal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, profeſſing before the moſt high God, My aime onely is Gods glory, the reſtoration of Gods rule and government, the peoples free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and happineſs, Judges freedom of conſcience from blood guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, the deliverance of the Nation from the now wrath of God, the Parliaments eternal honour in advancing truth and righteouſneſs: with theſe, and onely theſe deſires of ſoul, with <hi>Eſther,</hi> though ſhe knew the law of the king, to put to death any ſhall come within the inner, who is not called, except ſuch to whom the king holds out the golden Scepter, that he may live: <hi>But I have not been called to come in unto the king,</hi> Eſther 4.11. Verſ. 16. <hi>I will go in unto the king, which is not according to the law: if I periſh, I periſh.</hi> And as <hi>Mordecai,</hi> my ſoul tells me, <hi>If I altogether hold my peace at this time, deliverance ſhall ariſe to this people from another place, and I and my fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> The fear of God and his law that drove me, and the hope I had in you, as in men loving God, Juſtice, Righteouſneſs, and vowing to God and the people the ſame, with hands lifted up, to have your and the peoples freedome, being bound up in one, drew me to this ſervice; in which my hearts deſire is to ſerve you all, and be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your affectionately well-wiſhing ſervant in the ſervice of the Lord,</hi> John Brayne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:118573:44"/>
            <head>The Poſtſcript contains Objections and Reſolutions of what is ſaid againſt the Rule of the Law.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Quer.</hi> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Oth not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>Thoſe without law ſhall be judged without law?</hi> Rom. 2.12. then what need the laws government?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Some are without the letter and true ſence of the law, and the rule of it; as thoſe heathens, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who became a law unto themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Others are without the true ſence only, and not the letter; as <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Others without the rule, but not without the letter: and thus we are without the law this day.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Paul</hi> only without the true inward ſence of the law,
<note place="margin">a Minori ad Maius.</note> though not without the rule and government out-outwardly, and knowledge of the law, was yet ſaid to be <hi>without law;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much more may thoſe Nations who have the letter, and yet have not the rule and government of it, be ſaid to be <hi>without law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O remember, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. exhorted them <hi>not to receive the grace of God in vaine.</hi> You have the law in the Bible, which the heathens had not. O receive not ſo great a grace in vaine, ſo as not to rule by it: chuſing rather to be a law unto our ſelves, as thoſe heathens, who had not the knowledge of the law, then having the knowledge of the law, to have Gods will and law a law unto us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thoſe without law are ſaid to periſh without law:</hi> ſo that it is a ſad eſtate to be without the law.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though we are without the rule and judgement of the law, we
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:118573:44"/>are not without the knowledge of the law; we are under that; which will neceſſarly bring Judges and judged at laſt to be by God our Judge judged according to that, and our own law: for our law is no law with God.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>This is to make one ſhooe ſerve for every foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is there any ſhooe will fit our foot as that, nay but that that of Gods making? will not that of mans be it made as well may be? yea though it had the ſame in it as Gods, yet it wanted by far of that Gods, becauſe God made it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth not that that fits one nation, fit another? are we not all of the ſame nature? the unfitneſs muſt be either in reſpect of the law, or our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note.</hi> 1. The unfitneſs cannot be in the law; it hath all fitneſs of goodneſs, righteouſneſs, judgeth us with perfection; and ſo none is fit but this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor is the unfitneſs in the people. 1. They are ſinful, and need a law. 2. They are rational to underſtand the law. 3. They have deſires to ſerve God according the law. 4. They are lyable to puniſhment, if they obey not; and to whoſe more juſtly then to Gods?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Ye are not under the law, but grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> 1. Ye (that is, the believers at <hi>Rome,</hi> gathered out of the ſtate of the world, into fellowſhip with Chriſt in the ſtate of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, being by Chriſt redeemed from under the law) are not under the law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saying <hi>ye are not,</hi> the Scriptures imply, all but they in that eſtate thus redeemed were under the law, or the work thereof in their hearts: yea and they alſo, in the outward man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Object. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>What the law ſpeaks, it ſpeaks to thoſe that are under the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Now if any ſhall ſay we are under the law of God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why do we not reſt in the law, without ſetting up of laws of our own to judge by? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What other law, judgement, or puniſhment ought to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, but that, among thoſe are under the law?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We never nationally covenanted with God in it, nor was it ever nationally acknowledged to be our national rule and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor its form ſet up among us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we are under the law, what heathens in the world ever were not?</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:118573:45"/>
            <p n="1">1. They had law, which were the works of Gods law in their heart, as well as we.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They had this, when they had not the written law by them, as we have.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We having the law of God by us, to rule by, judge by, puniſh by; and yet ruling, judging and puniſhing by our own, we are worſe then the heathens, and by our traditions make void the law.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The heathens all had rule and government as we have, and laws as we have, and are yet ſaid to be without law, becauſe they governed not by the law of God; and ſo are we at this day.</p>
            <p>Again, if any ſhall ſay we are not under the law;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Queſtion is, Whether of right we ought not to be (or no.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or whether it be not prejudicious to Gods glory, and to his truth and the peoples proſperity, that they are not.</p>
            <p>If any ſay of right we ought not to be under the law;</p>
            <p n="1">1. As well might that man ſay, God ought not to rule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. People may do well enough without government, againſt that.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And there are no ſins, ſtrifes, controverſies, contentions among us; and ſo we need no juſtice, judgement, or puniſhment to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
            <p>If any ſay, Of right we ought not to be under the law of God, but out own;</p>
            <p n="1">1. By your traditions ye make voide the law of God; Gods is the law that hath authority and command onely: and indeed, in it yours are but traditions at beſt, which like <hi>Hagar</hi> ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up above <hi>Sarah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You having Gods law, ſhall be judged at laſt by it, and not your traditions: God will judge by it, and not yours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If our law be not according to Gods, we ſhall at laſt be judged for our judgement.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He that will not have Gods law to be his law, ſhall not have God to be his God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. before and with the giving of the laws covenant, he in it ſaith <hi>I am the Lord thy God:</hi> in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples taking of his law, they took him, and he them: and ſo he deals with all.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:118573:45"/>
            <p>If thou ſay, Of right we ought not to be under the law, but our traditions; for we have a long time been under them, and they are the beſt in the world:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The neerer they come to Gods, the better they are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But being not Gods, which onely is the Royal law;</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are not ſo good as his, nor to be compared with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are not to ſtand in competition with the Lords: if they do, man aſſumes the place of God to himſelf, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrones God: God will rule by none but his own: ſhall men again ſay they will not rule by others but their own?</p>
            <p n="3">3. To thoſe that ſay of this, or that, or any law, that its better then Gods, tell them it is blaſphemy to ſay ſo; and that man, as <hi>James</hi> 4.11. he ſpeaketh evil of the law, and judgeth the law, <hi>If thou judge the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge.</hi> Many ſuch Judges there are, and but few doers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If thou ſayeſt thy law is not ſo good as Gods, why doeſt thou not chuſe the beſt?</p>
            <p>O but we have been a long time under them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. So long thou haſt been without law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And without God in the way of the law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Ever ſince, many plagues have been heaped on the Nation, and multitudes of bleſſings detained from them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And other lords beſides <hi>Jehovah</hi> have tured over the Nation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The people have been under tyranny and oppreſſion, and many unjuſt traditions according to the will of men contrary to the will of God; as in the Acts repealed, and the mariage-money in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> paid <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the nation will beſt bear our own laws.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The corrupter a law is, the better natural people can indeed bear it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Every people that will be Gods, muſt bear his yoke,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The people will be bettered by bearing Gods, more then by bearing our own. Gods law will make an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> among men.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This objection agrees with that of God <hi>Ephraim is an heifer unaccuſtomed to the yoke;</hi> and ſo would for a while kick againſt the pricks.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That our evil nation will beſt bear our own laws, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>es not that the laws therefore are Gods; but againſt them, that they are therefore evil.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:118573:46"/>
            <p n="6">6. We are not to conſider what our Nation <hi>will</hi> bear, but what they <hi>ſhould</hi> bear; which is the law and yoak of God, and not men.</p>
            <p>Object. Others ſay. <hi>Something may be diminiſhed from the ſentence of the Law but nothing may be added.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolv.</hi> The one is expreſly forbid, as well the other, by the word and Law of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Joſua</hi> 23.6.</p>
            <p>Others will ſay. <hi>This is to be under Moſes, not Jeſus Chriſt; and to revive the Law again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Law was never deſtroyed; that is the Judicial and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, though the Ceremonial be: for Chriſt <hi>came not to deſtroy the Law, but to eſtabliſh it;</hi> which thou wouldſt have deſtroyed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As in in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> there was <hi>Moſes</hi> rule in the Jews Commonweal, and <hi>Aarons</hi> in the Temple; and theſe were diſtinct: ſo now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The like form we ſtill retain in our Church and State-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the State-government ought to be that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God he gave no other; and Chriſt ſaith he deſtroyed not that: the Church government now is changed from that of <hi>Aarons</hi> in Prieſthood. Miniſtry. Adminiſtrations, and Rule; ſo that now it is <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt: before, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ruled.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe under Chriſt are ſo far from being without law as that the law is more excellently opened and taught, in a more ſpiritual way then <hi>Moſes</hi> taught, or the people under <hi>Moſes</hi> could bear. This is cleared Mat. 5.27. <hi>Ye have heard it hath been ſaid to thoſe of old,</hi> (That is thoſe firſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> time covenanted with God in the law by <hi>Moſes) Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery,</hi> verſ. 28. <hi>But I</hi> (that is, Chriſt) <hi>ſay unto you, He that looketh on a woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adultery with her in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence under Chriſt in the Goſpel-eſtate, God is ſaid to <hi>Judge the ſecrets of men according to the Goſpel</hi> Rom. 2.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God by the law under <hi>Moſes</hi> judgeth the acts of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man done in the fleſh againſt the law, and ſets downe the judgement and puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heace <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Tim. 5.27. <hi>The ſins of ſome are open before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand and go before to Judgement;</hi> under <hi>Moſes: others fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after;</hi> under the judgement of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſtion is, Whether law of God be not as abſolutely neceſſary to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:118573:46"/>rule and govern men in the civil Eſtate, as in the other of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether it be not as unlawful to ſet up a law contrary to God in the one, as in the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it be not the proper authority of God, to give laws to men in the one, as well as the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and the law ſet men on doing, Chriſt on doing: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot do the law, therefore to believe; aſſuring us that in that we ſhall receive the promiſe, and be freed from the curſe of the law likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Note,</hi> This Chriſt manifeſts, that Judgement of external acts againſt the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was left to <hi>Moſes, Luk.</hi> 12, 13, 14. the man that came to have the inheritance divided, to Chriſt, had this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Who made me a Judge or a Divider?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In the woman taken in the act of Adultery. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.3, 4, 56. Chriſt he would not accuſe nor condemne her: for now when <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> was come, the Scepter was departed. Again, the woman was <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed</hi> not <hi>abſolved,</hi> becauſe there was no accnſers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Some ſay there is not the like ſeverity uſed under the Goſpel as under the law in judgement againſt ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> This was the firſt ground of the Manichean Hereſie: for in making difference between the proceedings of Juſtice under the Law and the Goſpel againſt ſin, you lay a foundation for the ſetting forth of two Gods; one ſevere, the other merciful.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Goſpel doth not mitigate, but aggravate ſin, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt did not deſtroy the law, nor mitigate the puniſhment to any unbeliever, of what is ſet down in the law: nay, if a believer fall into theſe ſins and he ſuffer in the body, it is <hi>that his ſoul may be ſaved in the day of the Lord.</hi> The inceſtuous perſon was not put to death the Church having not that power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> The preventing grace of God keeps the believer from <hi>the ſin that is unto death</hi> Joh. 15.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If it be mitigated men ſhould do well to ſhew from the mouth of God in what it was mitigated to whom, and whether to all or ſome ſinne onely; and why not to all, as well as ſome: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in the command, or in the ſtatute, or the puniſhment, or in all: and how it can be in any one of theſe, and not in all and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:118573:47"/>each of them: or how this can be under the Goſpel, and not be by Chriſt: and how he 1. eſtabliſheth the law, 2. and doth not deſtroy it in part, more then many Iota's or tittles, though not in whole.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If it be ſtrictly examined, there is more ſeverity then Gods law alloweth of in ſome of our now laws; and in ſome leſs: in which both there is injuſtice committed, according to the meaſure we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> from the law of God, either to the right hand or to the left.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is to be obſerved, that the Judges deſigned to hear difficult cauſes, which were not clear to the other Judges, were not to give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teace of their owne; they were to do it according to the ſentence of the law. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.11. which ſhews clearly this, that where the law is not expreſly declared concerning a caſe in hand, that it may be is unuſal among men, there,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That caſe is to be referred to theſe Judges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe Judges muſt judge according to the ſentence of the law, though not in ſome, yet in facts of the like nature with that.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They were to ſhew the ſentence out of the law, and to teach it them, if they underſtood it not.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then, and not untill then, they were to put the ſentence in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If upon all this, the man ſhould preſumptuouſly refuſe to hearken and obey, and ſay he was not to do it, the man was to be put to death.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This courſe was not to be taken, but onely then and in that caſe, when it was not clearly reſolved in the word to all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> Is this; To thoſe which ſay many caſes are not ſet downe in the word, nor can it be a rule to judge by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> It is granted: yet is there proviſion made to remedy that, by the Judges aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>How is the law perfect then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Judges ſhall find the thing ſentenced in the law, though not under that name, in ſome ſin of the ſame kinde, from which they muſt not decline: the law, like the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> will tell them, and ſhew the judgement to them; when they have a cauſe to require thereat.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Law ſaith, men muſt not turn from the right hand or left thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> True: Thoſe that know the law in the known cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:118573:47"/>are not to decline from that; nor are the Judges concerning the obſcure caſes to decline that ſentence of the law that doth accord therewith in the book of God, though it be not particularly ſet downe, and nominally expreſſed, and added to that iniquity par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>David committed Adultery and Murther, and was not ſlain: which was a type of more mercy to be miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel then under the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Some will ſay. <hi>David</hi> being King and ſupream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, there was none under that government then would judge him: but God did judge him in his houſe, his wife, his children; as in the Story is ſet forth abundantly after.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And more truly, <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery and Murther was ſo hid, that there were no witneſſes appeared to accuſe him; and though God knew it, few in the world elſe did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.12. but theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented thereunto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>David</hi> marryed <hi>Bathſheba</hi> after; which indeed did ſeem to be according to the law; but being a Whore, it was not, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.9, 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> was a type of Chriſt in many things.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God might diſpence with his law for wonderful ſweet ends, and good for us, though by ſuch wayes, as we underſtand not the juſtneſs of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If men writing the Scriptures had not had our fallings and been ſubject to our temptations, we could not have had that comfort now we may have in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God ſuffering them to fall, would not with their fall take them away: that had not been a ſupport, but terror.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this God would ſhew, that though the bodies of thoſe (for ſuch like ſins) ſuffer, yet they believing and repenting, their ſouls may be ſaved in the day of the Lord. So that the uſe hereof is good, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good to thoſe that do ſuffer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Many of the Saints, as <hi>David,</hi> are guilty ſecretly of theſe fins; and were it not for <hi>David,</hi> would have ſorrow without hope, as it were.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By <hi>Nathan</hi> God having diſcovered his ſin, and he repenting, God is ſaid to <hi>put away his ſin,</hi> that he ſhould not dye, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:118573:48"/>
            <p n="1">1. Here is the putting away of his ſin, which upon repentance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others may do, and yet not be freed from death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here expreſly is not onely one, but the other alſo by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet from God revealed, that it ſhould be made good to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God puniſhed him in his houſe, his wives, his children, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The ſcepter ſhall not depart from</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>nor the Law-giver from between his feet,</hi> &amp;c. ſo there was a Law-giver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. This was ſpoken before the Law was given, where men made Laws.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The word for <hi>Law-giver,</hi> ſignifies a Scribe. If any ſhould give the Law, he had the Scepter, and not him, between his feet.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This <hi>he</hi> between the Kings Feet, was but an aſſiſtant to him, to ſhew him what the Law was in caſes brought before him, out of the Law of God, which was to be alwaies by the King.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>O that when the Covenant was ſent to the Nation, it had been done according to the minde of God! that is, as Covenants were when nationally by Kings and People made with God, <hi>viz.</hi> by taking the law, the Statutes and Judgements of God, to be our law, and to be ruled and judged by it onely; and take God with the law to be our God, and all other law to be laid aſide and known no more of us: ſo had we done the work of God, and a heavenly bleſſing would have followed it. Since which, the effects of that ignorant blinde Covenant have been nothing but confuſion, diviſion, war, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our ſelves and others. O ye Princes and People, though ye are in all theſe, yet if you will obey and receive the Lord and his law this day, ye ſhall be healed of all your confuſed diſtempers, and be ſaved, 1 King. 8.57. <hi>The Lord our God be with us, as he was with our Fathers; let him not leave us nor forſake us,</hi> verſ. 58. <hi>That he may incline our hearts unto him, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his Commandments and his Statutes, and his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he commanded our Fathers.</hi> Deut. 5.29. <hi>That it may be well with us, and our children after us for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:118573:48"/>
               <p>And ye, O ye Univerſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a viſitation from above is drawing near, to viſit you; and the moſt juſt God the viſitor, who will judge you according to the judgement of the great Where. Ye can now no longer delude nor captivate men with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences: for God will take you away, and ſet up wayes of learning of his own.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Your riſe was from the Pope, even <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Theodoſious,</hi> twelve Cardinals, and multitudes of Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about the year 423.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You by being governed and advanced, and educated by his adherents, and ſet up to accompliſh his ends, came to be the onely means to make void the order of the Church; who firſt choſe her Miniſtry out of her owne ſocieties and members, but now are taken out of the Univerſity, be they what they will, and put on them whether they will or not; to the utter extirpation of the Churches priviledge: by which encourgement to learning and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in all the Church-members, was taken away, to encourage ſuch as made a trade of it in the Univerſity, the Church-members reſting on their teaching onely, and never reſpected any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of teaching to be obtained by themſelves in the now Church-way, the Church being robbed of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You plead for your practice the Scripture, as if it were your pattern. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.3. there were ſons of the Prophets at <hi>Bethel;</hi> and ver. 4. there were more at <hi>Iericho</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.20. a company of Prophets are ſtanding, and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtanding as appointed over them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe Sons of the Prophets were ſuch as were educated in the writings of the Prophets, and read them and did more eactly diſcuſs the Myſtereis thereof, then in the Synagogues. Thoſe bred in theſe, houſes were immediately fitted for the Synagouge-xe hortation and reading.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt of their education was reading, and well underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, as writing; and this fitted him as a Scribe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. After this, they were taught the ſence and meaning of the word, either in the literal or hiſtorical, the prophetical or typical part of it: and then they came to be diſputers of the law, or Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees; in which order <hi>Paul</hi> was.</p>
               <p n="4">4. God uſually rayſed up of theſe (that faithfully gave themſelves to the ſtudy of the Law, and taught it) Prophets to foretell things to come; as <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Samuel.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:118573:49"/>
               <p>And thoſe other hundred Prophets mentioned 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.13. in which places, thoſe that were Prophets, for confirmation of their propheſies and call, did uſually teach, as appears: <hi>Elias</hi> he is ſent to <hi>Bethel,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.2. at <hi>Bethel</hi> it is without queſtion he taught in that School, and among the reſt told the Children of the Prophets, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. that the Lord would take him away (being <hi>Eliſhas</hi> Maſter) from his head that day: and the ſame being ſent to <hi>Jericho,</hi> in verſ. 4.5. where the Jews received that tradition of his teaching in their Schools, that <hi>Elias ſhall firſt come,</hi> Matth. 17.10, 11.</p>
               <p>That paſſage of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.20, 24. was an extraordinary caſe, to preſerve <hi>David,</hi> in which <hi>Saul</hi> and his ineſſengers were changed; as before in <hi>Eſau,</hi> when he came againſt <hi>Jacob;</hi> and that of <hi>Sauls</hi> meeting the Prophets, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.3, 5. which were given him for ſignes to confirm him by, in Gods electing of him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Theſe Schools were in all Towns uſually, as our Grammar-Schools are, having onely the reading of the Law and the Prophets uſed among them; who were according to their ſeveral capacities taught and diſtinguiſhed, as in our Schools by forms and places, one from the other.</p>
               <p>In which, nor <hi>Cato,</hi> nor <hi>Virgil,</hi> nor <hi>Homer,</hi> nor <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> were not uſually read; but the commands of God; by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof God was honoured, and they ſanctified.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In this ſtudy and ſociety, God would manifeſt himſelf, when he would not in the obſcene readings of <hi>Ovid,</hi> and the lying fables of the other Poets.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In this teaching men were not devoted hereunto onely, but had other callings to employ themſelves in to live by; and were taught alſo in theſe Schools one part of the day: as <hi>Paul,</hi> brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> was by his profeſſion a Tent-maker.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Out of the Word, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> and other natural Philoſophy, may be deduced with Tropes, Metaphors, and Figures; <hi>Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie</hi> &amp;c. by which men may be better acquainted with the Word, then now they are. This is the wiſdom of a people, and not the knowledge of the cuſtom of Heathens, which onely tends to make men ſuch, and juſtifies them.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Lawyers hereby may be made, and rightly fitted to judge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:118573:49"/>
               <p n="10">10. Every man is rightly taught to live in their youth according to Gods law; as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 11 9.9, &amp; 98, &amp; 99. verſes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Now if they offend, they dye more juſtly, being taught the ſence and ſentence of the law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> Ye Univerſities, the wrath of God will break out upon you; your dayes are numbred, and your time neer come, in which you will ſee that it is not a reformation will ſerve your turn, or ſave you from the decree.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ye princes of the people in Parliament, a people are rude without learning; O be intreated to convert ſufficient maintenance to the maintaining of ſome freely to teach in all towns.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To teach the Hebrew reading to ſome.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To teach the moral or judicial law to others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The prophets to others, and their meaning.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To teach the Greek; and in thoſe ſchools only read the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Jeſus Chriſt, written by <hi>Matthew, Marke,</hi> &amp;c. with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As for Latine, and the long time ſpent in obtaining thereof, the time is coming that the authors and learning laid up in their writings, will be of little or no uſe to the world: God will inſtruct them with better of his own. The time is coming, knowledge ſhall cover the earth, as water the ſeas: and all thoſe mighty Libraries be but loſt matter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is as a bage of the Roman conqueſt, which will ceaſe with that Empire in a maner amongſt us; the laws and true learning being turned into our own language.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this means, in the meetings on the ſeventh day ſabbath, the gifts and knowledge of every particular perſon, either in his exact reading of the law, or underſtanding of the myſtery or propheſie of the prophets, comes to be made uſe of and exerciſed; they being herein a nation of Prieſts, and ſo would beget much wiſdome and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation for knowledge in every man, and comfort in every man by ſeeing and knowing the gifts and profittings of his children in the law, who would come to be ſpurs and goads to provoke the elder to a more diligent ſearch of the law, and knowledge thereof that they may not be under the teaching of children that they ſhall ſpeak, and themſelves be dumbe; they going beyond the elders in deſcribing the hiſtory, and in opening the myſteries of the law and prophets. In this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:118573:50"/>eſtate of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or mens being under the law, was no prieſthood at all; yet <hi>is he preached every ſeventh day,</hi> Acts 15.21. when and where the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> teaching, did what he could to make men from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt in a right and true way, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.21. whence, though <hi>many are called few are choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The prieſthood in the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> belonged to the temple, and was conferred on <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons, who taught not the law in the Synagogues: thoſe that taught there, ſate in <hi>Moſes,</hi> not <hi>Aarons</hi> chaire, or prieſtly ſucceſſion, <hi>Moſes</hi> being before <hi>Aaron, Jer.</hi> 7.22, 23.</p>
               <p>The which prieſthood ceaſing, and another, even that of Chriſts, being now inſtituted of God, and ſet up in the place thereof in the Church, called from <hi>Moſes,</hi> conſiſting of believers; which was given to the Apoſtles and their true ſucceſſors, to adminiſter under the Lord Jeſus; which call no man was to take on him, but according to the Lords inſtitutions; who were to attend on that place of miniſtry: whereas Evangeliſts, paſtors, or teachers, as they were called to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before the Lord under Jeſus Chriſt, who were not to be cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred about any worldly occaſions, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>Luk. 9.33. <hi>Let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, one for</hi> Moſes, <hi>one for</hi> Elias.</p>
               <p>The tabernacle was the place God firſt had his worſhip ſet up in, under <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and here ſignifieth moveableneſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſervice of God under <hi>Moſes,</hi> and under the law, is meant, under tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tabernacle for <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſervice of God under Chriſt and grace, is meant by the tabernacle <hi>for thee,</hi> or Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which adminiſtrations falling, in the hiding of the Church, are againe to be reſtored in our dayes by that <hi>Elias,</hi> in that taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle is attributed to him.</p>
               <p>How men came from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſts adminiſtration, is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently ſet forth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1, 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> diſciples were taught the letter of the ten commands: Chriſt taught his diſciples the commands, in the ſpiritual part of it, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. which are called by Chriſt <hi>my commands;</hi> in which his diſciples were to walk with God, in a more holy and more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable way: which commands the world could not receive.</p>
               <p>In the New Teſtament, three Scriptures reſpect Magiſtrates ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream and ſubordinate.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:118573:50"/>
               <p n="1">1. The which are kings and their deputies, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>The powers that be (viz.</hi> Nero's and his deputies) <hi>are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God.</hi> Thus 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>to kings, as ſupreme,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>or to governors, as to them that are ſent by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. God ordained no powers, but Kings and Judges; and the Kings of the Nations, from whom the Jews took their pattern came to receive a ſtability in their place by it, during the time of the fourth, or the Roman Monarchy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When men deſtroy Monarchy, they muſt return to Judges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as at firſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. or the power cannot be ſaid, as the heathen power had ſaid of it, <hi>that it was of God;</hi> God ſetting up no other publike forme of Rule, but that, to govern a nation by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Kings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.13. He ſhews what the rule of Monarchy was, or was to be in their law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. He ſhews what the authority was in the rulers executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their then law, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. how the power, during its time of ſtanding; by which authority and rule were kept alive, and not to be infeſted until that time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 24. when <hi>all</hi> of the then <hi>rule, authority, and power, is to be put down,</hi> by the ſtone cut out of the mount without hands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.44 45. which is done in part, and now doing this day.</p>
               <p n="5">5. On this onely ground, becauſe it was <hi>ordained of God,</hi> and <hi>an ordinance of God,</hi> though they were Gentiles, and <hi>without law,</hi> onely being <hi>a law to themſelves,</hi> verſ. 5. The Apoſtle ſhews they ſhould <hi>be ſubject, not only for wrath, but conſcience ſake,</hi> even to the laws called <hi>ordinances of men.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To theſe Kings as to the Kings of Iſrael, tribute and cuſtome were paid; which was not under the Judges: which ſhows it the freeſt government, and beſt for the people: which concerns you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in reſpect of the truſt repoſed in you.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The renewing of the kingdom from Judges to kings, is to be done when from Kings to Judges, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.14. &amp; 8.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.17. This law owns not ſuits about hunting, hawking, killing of fowl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor allows no ſuch game to treſpaſs other men, and appoints labour rather to all, and condemns ſuch exerciſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets idleneſs and beggery in a Commonweal, drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that it is as neceſſary to deſtroy thoſe vermin, the hawks and hounds,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:118573:51"/>as heretofore wolves: the one deſtroyed cattel, the other men. And in ſtead of ſhooting at Pigeons, Oh how good were it the houſes were ſhot down! Here is no law for Tythes, nor offering, nor for a mans turning aſide occaſionally to paſs over another mans ground; nor about Wills and Teſtaments; nor to ſatisfie mens revenge, to vex their neighbours with Law: but, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.8. <hi>Go not forth haſtily to ſtrive leſt thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to ſhame: debate thy cauſe with thy neighbour himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 7.12. <hi>Do unto all men as you would men ſhould do unto you; that is the law and the Prophets.</hi> So that great men by Law and Prophets are to do no other to the poor, then they would the poor ſhould do to them: there muſt be the ſame law and liberty to the one, as to the other, or it is not a Common-weal: one muſt not keep any thing to oppreſs hurt, or hinder another man, much leſs many men, onely to ſatisfie their luſts.</p>
               <p>As for the State of <hi>Venice,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As other Gentiles, they are a Law to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the people chuſe their Judges, yet they judging by Laws of their own, their Government is not of God, nor is it eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed of Gods, as that of Kings was among Gentiles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bland us</hi> ſayth, that the liberty of the <hi>Venetians</hi> to govern by their own Laws, was granted them by the great and high Biſhop of Rome, <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That their Government is not of God, appears by their allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of publike Stews in their Commonweal, worſe then which the Heathens have not done; and the converting of the hire of whores to a publike uſe: a great abomination.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nor are their Judges, as Judges at the firſt, ſet up in the gates of every City: ſo that that Government, with the reſt of the Papal powers, will ceaſe and fall.</p>
               <p>The fall of the Romane Monarchy under the ſeventh Head, or feet mixt with Iron and Clay, as it was under Pope and Kings:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt ſtep began in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth's deſtroying the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of the Pope, and ruling alone, <hi>anno</hi> 1531.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the United Eſtates of <hi>Holland,</hi> caſting down of the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> but ruling by the States General and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, as by Lords and Commons: which alſo will be in its time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:118573:51"/>
               <p n="3">3. In this Nation, this Parliament have depoſed King and Lords, the Commons onely having the power of rule in their hands; and ſo have made a ſtep beyond them therein.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth is, that the Souldier take down the Law, Rule, or Government that is, and ſet up God's, by <hi>Judges as at firſt:</hi> in which, the grand Mutations of the worlds affairs come to centre, and receive fixedneſs under God, (the Kingdom being the Lords) and the earth becomes abundantly bleſſed, with all therein, by the ſame thouſand yeers, when Tyranny ſprings again; and Time quickly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath its end.</p>
               <p>The main ground and reaſon why the four Monarchies are ſet out by Beaſts, ariſing out of a neceſſity occaſioned by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among men <hi>Dau.</hi> 7. by which the world, like another Sea, was fill'd full of troubles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Babylonian, ſet out by the Lion, verſ. 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Medes and Perſian, by the Bear, verſ. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Greek, by the Leopard, verſ. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Romane is not expreſſed by its <hi>form,</hi> but by its <hi>nature,</hi> to be a Beaſt dreadful, terrible, ſtrong, having iron teeth, devouring and breaking in pieces, and ſtamping the reſt with her feet, and being diverſe from all beaſts, lively ſet out by <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 13.2. like a leopard in colour, having feet like a bear, the mouth of a lion; and the dragon gave him his power: from whence he takes the place, power, authority, and name of the dragon.</p>
               <p>Note the name of Beaſt: for Government and Authority is not given them, but for the kinde of Rule and Law that they had among themſelves, which was according to their luſts, and not of God; they making their luſts a law, and ſo become a law to themſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence the Heathens, without the Law and rule of God, are ſaid <hi>not to be a people.</hi> Deut. 32.21. Rom. 10.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Heathen Empires, ſet out by the Beaſts: 1. The Kings were the horns; the Councels of the kingdoms, the heads; the Laws and Lawyers, the teeth; the Executioners the feet; the common people, the body, and the Pope riding on them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The beſt alluſion given the four Monarchies, was that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> which is likened to a man: when that man that had the viſion, and who repreſented the golden head, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.33. was driven from
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:118573:52"/>among men, loſt his reaſon, feeds with beaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which is ſet forth, what the men were, while without the rule of God, and what would be the end the Monarchs of the world at laſt would come unto: Thus the Pſalm, <hi>Man that is in honour, and underſtands not,</hi> (that is, how to rule and govern according to God) <hi>is like the beaſts that periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Jewes were therefore called <hi>a People,</hi> becauſe they had a God, and were guided by his laws, and ſought the good of one another, and not the hurt, as the afore-mentioned beaſts, who were ſuch as lived by preying one on another: the worſt of all which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, was the laſt of the Roman Monarchy; which under the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, rule, and power thereof, is ſtill the beaſt fore-ſpoken of.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The queſtion is, whether a ſociety of men altering that law, and ſetting up any other beſides that of Gods under God and ſet up other authority and power then that of Gods, as ſet downe in the Scripture be not a beaſt in Gods account ſtill, though another beaſt from that which was before. Not that I ſay there ſhall be any; for there are to be but four beaſts or Monarchies: the fifth ſhall be the dominion of Chriſt, when the Saints ſhall rule the world.</p>
               <p>Que. <hi>If the judicial law be not equally a rule to govern a Commonweal by as the Goſpel is to rule the Church by; on the ſame grounds and reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Que. <hi>If it be not an abomination before God while men have his law to ſet up</hi> Jus humanum (<hi>if any ſuch things were) in the place of</hi> Jus divinum <hi>being the act of Antichriſt</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. <hi>who was without law, ſetting himſelf in place of God, making law of his owne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Que. <hi>If there can be any ſafety to judge by our law ſeeing God will judge all men by his owne that have his law, as we ſay we have,</hi> Rom. 2.12, 13.</p>
               <p>As for war, it was</p>
               <p n="1">1. Referred to men choſen therefore; and the Judges took no cognizance of it in judgement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The laws and directions therefore were particular, and diſtinct from the judicial law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This war againſt Antichriſt being Gods, as that againſt <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek,</hi> both having their time and fulneſs of ſin expired; the rules for the one are rules for the other in an eminent way: which ought not by the General and the Councel of the Nation for war be paſſed by,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:118573:52"/>leſt it become our ſin, and we in the end ſuffer for it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Inquire into the reaſon why the plague is fallen ſo heavy on the Souldiers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ye ſhall find it is of God, for their not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his judgement.</p>
               <p>This general poſition is to be concluded on; <hi>That whatſoever is not properly comprehended under one of the ten Commands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not unto the judicial law, but the ceremonial; as Tythes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>That that is referred to any of the commands, muſt be for judgement and rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Quer. <hi>If now there be any ground to us, that the ſale of lands ſhould be onely for</hi> 50 <hi>years to the Jubilce; or if that were meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ceremonial, or in a mixt law,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It did ſhadow out the reſtoration of mans fallen eſtate by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt was to begin his miniſtry then, under whom was to be a ſpecial freedome of what was under the law or <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Morality (ſay ſome) appears of this, in that,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is under the eighth Command, <hi>Thou ſhaltnot ſteal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Or under the tenth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The equity of this ceaſeth, in that all had of that land part, but few have of this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God laid a ſpecial claim to that more then any.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Que. If God layes not the ſame to the lands of others, becauſe judged of God, forfeited, caſt out, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Pro.</hi> That Law God Judges by, is the fitteſt law for judgement.</p>
               <p>But this is the law God judgeth by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is the fitteſt law for judgement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Where Judgement is not Gods, it is not true.</p>
               <p>But where the law is not Gods, the judgement is not his, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. If to make laws, when we have the law of God, be not againſt the law and God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Againſt God, taking away his prerogative.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Againſt the law, making that void, having but the name of law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this means men are in the place of God, and God hath no place among us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> When men judge by the law of God, judgement is Gods, and not elſe: but in this Nation men judge not by the law of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> As the law and judgement ſhould be Gods, ſo the authority ſhould be his.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:118573:53"/>
            <head>Additional.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Two things I had forgot to clear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Lawyers, as <hi>Zenas,</hi> in <hi>Titus</hi> 3.13. and thoſe others mentioned in <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> were of divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and ſerve at all to prove the Lawyers and their now-practice among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. <hi>Their inſtitution is not in the law, as an officer of the court; but aroſe among the reſt of corruptions among the Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They expounded the law in the Synagogues and not plead it in the gate of judicature before the Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>They cleared or interpreted difficulties in the divine law only, and ſerves not to prove a practice of men undertaking to plead the laws of nature or of nations, but ſhews that their law and pleadings make void Gods and its diſpenſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>As for</hi> Joſeph <hi>the counſellor, he was a counſellor of the Jews republick, one of their ſeventy, that counſelled by the law of God, and not of men; in a way for publike ſafety, not private gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Or it may be he was a counſellor to the Roman eſtate becauſe in favour ſo much with Pilate.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Second concerns widdows.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why in dividing the ſtate, they had ſo little of what was left by their deceaſed husbands.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>She was to return to her fathers houſe again, as in</hi> Tamar, Gen. 38.10. Remain a widdow at thy fathers houſe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 22.13. If the Prieſts daughter be a widdow, or divorced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to her fathers houſe, as in her youth, ſhe ſhall eat of her fathers meat. <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.10. <hi>ſpeaks of the widdows vow and if ſhe vowed it in her husbands houſe or dayes, as appears in the</hi> 11 verſ. <hi>and he heard it: which ſhews, after his death ſhe left that was his houſe, and went to her fathers; yet her children were
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:118573:53"/>not to forſake, but help her alſo, of ſhe needed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>If her father was living; if dead, ſhe had part if her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers inheritance, that that came to her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>God made ſpecial proviſion for the deſolate or widdows by many ſpecial laws</hi> Deut. 16.14. <hi>they had part of the harveſt,</hi> Deut. 24.19, 20.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The widdows were provided for out of the ſtore of Gods houſe, that is, the tythes,</hi> Deut. 12, 26.13. &amp; 24.19. <hi>which was paid once in three yeers only; where they came and fetched it; and was a reproachful eſtate,</hi> Iſa. 54.4.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Queſt.</hi> If Miniſters be not now ſo to be maintained. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, I leave you to a particular Treatiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Queſt.</hi> If widdows and orphans be not that way to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for.</p>
               <p>Reſp. <hi>Yea, by bringing in a ſufficient portion thereof every three yeers into ſome publike place, for relief of the poor widdow and orphans, and others, and ſome intruſted to deliver it out to them as need requires.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is not other ways as good as this?</p>
               <p>Reſp. <hi>No, becauſe this is commanded; which man is not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> If in caſes of juſtice, as an eye for eye tooth for tooth a man may not take 100 <hi>l.</hi> ſatisfaction, and free his adverſary.</p>
               <p>Reſp. 1. <hi>The Judge is but an executioner of the wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>He is bound to do what the law ſays; that is his rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He is not to Judgo the law, and its equity or rigour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>He is not to decline the will of God, for expedients of men,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The law is for terror to others, as well as for doing right to whom wrong is done at preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Gods juſtice is to be ſatisfyed on the offender, as well as the damage of the ſufferer ſatisfyed: of which much more may be ſaid; but this I conceive to be ſufficient to prove care herein muſt be had, that men make not the law of God void by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or practices in judgement of their own, in which men actually forſake God, and come to be forſaken of him; to the ruine of the generations of the world; which they that are wiſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:118573:54"/>will fear, and be faithful to God: which the Lord make the men of this generation to do, and the people will be free and happy in the governors thereof, yea and in God: to whom be obedience and glory for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
